<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle written (dated the 30th of the 11th month 1659,) and sent from London into the countrey. By a friend to the glorious (though at this day despised) cause of Christ, in answer to a letter sent up to him (dated the 16th of the same month) wherein the following things are treated of, (viz.) 1. The fifth kingdom it self, which the God of Heaven sets up in the latter dayes. 2. The kingdom of the beast which is to be destroyed. 3. The instruments that are to be used in destroying the one and erecting the other; with the way or manner how they are to be used. 4. The time of the beginning of this work. [bracket] First, before Christs personal comming. Secondly, before the call of the Jewes. Thirdly, that it is already begun, and hath taken place in this nation and that Cromwel with the army, hath apostatized from it, and that all the powers, or governments that have been set up since that time, have been, and still are upon the foundation of the apostacy. As also, severall of the particular evills which the army, and others abetting the apostacy are guilty of. Together with, some considerations tendered to the favourers of Christ's righteous cause, wherein is laid down, their duty of separation from Babylon, and from all the parts and branches (both in church and state) of the forementioned apostacy.</title>
            <author>N. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09926</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 124064265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S119B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">124064265</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 124064265</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192321</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192321)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2915:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle written (dated the 30th of the 11th month 1659,) and sent from London into the countrey. By a friend to the glorious (though at this day despised) cause of Christ, in answer to a letter sent up to him (dated the 16th of the same month) wherein the following things are treated of, (viz.) 1. The fifth kingdom it self, which the God of Heaven sets up in the latter dayes. 2. The kingdom of the beast which is to be destroyed. 3. The instruments that are to be used in destroying the one and erecting the other; with the way or manner how they are to be used. 4. The time of the beginning of this work. [bracket] First, before Christs personal comming. Secondly, before the call of the Jewes. Thirdly, that it is already begun, and hath taken place in this nation and that Cromwel with the army, hath apostatized from it, and that all the powers, or governments that have been set up since that time, have been, and still are upon the foundation of the apostacy. As also, severall of the particular evills which the army, and others abetting the apostacy are guilty of. Together with, some considerations tendered to the favourers of Christ's righteous cause, wherein is laid down, their duty of separation from Babylon, and from all the parts and branches (both in church and state) of the forementioned apostacy.</title>
                  <author>N. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: N.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Toronto Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fifth Monarchy Men --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192321:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE Written (dated the 30th of the 11th Month 1659,) and ſent from LONDON INTO THE COUNTREY.</p>
            <p>By a Friend to the Glorious (though at this Day deſpiſed) <hi>CAUSE OF CHRIST,</hi> in Anſwer to a Letter ſent up to him [Dated the 16th of the ſame Month] Wherein the following Things are Treated of, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>FIFTH KINGDOM</hi> it ſelf, which the God of Heaven ſets up in the latter Dayes.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>KINGDOM</hi> of the <hi>BEAST</hi> which is to be deſtroyed.</item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Inſtruments</hi> that are to be uſed in deſtroying the one and erecting the other; with the way or manner how they are to be uſed.</item>
               <item>4. The <hi>Time</hi> of the beginning of this <hi>Work.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Before <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal comming.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Before the <hi>Call</hi> of the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That it is already begun, and hath taken place in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and that <hi>Cromwel</hi> with the Army, hath Apoſtatized from it, and that all the <hi>Powers,</hi> or <hi>Governments</hi> that have been ſet up ſince that time, have been, and ſtill are upon the Foundation of the Apoſtacy.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>AS ALSO, Severall of the Particular Evills which the Army, and others abetting the Apoſtacy are guilty of.</p>
            <p>Together with, Some CONSIDERATIONS tendered to the <hi>Favourers</hi> of <hi>CHRIST'S RIGHTEOUS CAUSE,</hi> wherein is laid down, their duty of Seperation from <hi>BABYLON,</hi> and from all the <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Branches</hi> (both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi>) of the forementioned Apoſtacy.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 145.11.</bibl> They ſhall ſpeak of the Glory of thy Kingdom, and talk of thy Power.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Hoſ. 6.3.</bibl> Then ſhall ye know, if you follow on to know the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Rev. 18.14.</bibl> Come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192321:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192321:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle written dated the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the 11th Month 1659. and ſent from <hi>London</hi> into the Countrey, by a Friend to the <hi>Glorious</hi> (though at this day deſpiſed) <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> in Anſwer to a Letter ſent up to him, dated the 16th of the ſame Moneth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THine of the 16th inſtant, I have received, with thy earneſt deſires of my giving thee ſome account of my judgment about the matters of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom;</hi> I am glad that any of the Saints are enquiring after thoſe glorious Truths that appertain to the exaltation of <hi>Zions King</hi> in the latter days; It is no ſmall matter of grief, that thoſe things which are ſo high in the Fathers eſteem and purchaſed by Chriſt his precious blood, ſhould be ſo much deſpiſed and trampled under Foot by the Profeſſors of this Generation and that thoſe which own, and witneſs for it, ſhould be ſo much reproached, yea dealt with as <hi>tranſgreſſors,</hi> as it is at this day. But for my ſelf, I have been through grace made to rejoyce, and to count it no ſmall honour, to have my name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation offered up yea buryed with the precious <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and am contented in the hopes of a ſhare in the Reſurrection of that <hi>Cauſe;</hi> But that I may come to anſwer thy deſires, I ſhall lay down two things by way of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Matters of this <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> are very Deep and Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11. and the coming of it, not with obſervation, but <hi>as a Thief, Luke</hi> 17.20. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8. And the Antichriſtian State, (which is to be deſtroyed by, and ſo way made for this <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> to take place) is very Deep and Myſterious alſo; It is called the <hi>Myſtery of iniquity,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The underſtanding of theſe Myſteries, are not attained by the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Arts, Parts or Witt of Men, no nor by any holineſs or vertue of ours but is a free gift of God, effected by the Leadings and Teachings of his holy Spirit in whomſoever he pleaſeth, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. <hi>Math.</hi> 11, 25, 26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3. Chap. 21.10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. And as to my ſelf, I have been brought under ſo much ſenſe of my ignorance and darkneſs in thoſe deep Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that I have been ſometimes aſhamed to appear in publick to ſpeak of them, fearing that I might rather Eclipſe then open thoſe bleſſed truths, yet I dare not ſay that I have been left without a meaſure of the leadings of the Spirit in theſe things, but it hath been in ſuch untrodden paths, and attended with ſuch great difficulties both from within, and from not only the World, but many of my dear friends (whom for holineſs and underſtanding I have preferred above many) that I have been ready to ſay with <hi>Joſhua</hi> Chap. 7.7. <hi>Would to God I had been content, and dwelt on the other ſide;</hi> And with <hi>Jeremiah</hi> Chap. 15.10. <hi>Wo is me my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192321:3"/>
that thou haſt borne me a Man of ſtrife, and a man of contention to the whole earth;</hi> But I dare not allow my ſelf in ſuch Complaints, leaſt I ſhould offend the Lord.</p>
            <p>Though my darkneſs and weakneſs would diſcourage me in this undertaking, yet the conſideration of the many falſe reports and miſtakes that have been, and ſtill are among the Churches about thoſe Principles, which both my ſelf and divers others have been helped to own in this evil day and the conſideration of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtumbling-blocks that hath been by thoſe reports caſt in the way of ſeveral of the Lords Children and the endeavours to poſſeſs them with prejudice againſt the <hi>Righteous Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> doth help me over all the diſcouragements to preſent unto thee (not only for thy ſelf, but the reſt of my dear friends with thee) in all plainneſs, what my underſtanding is;</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, Of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> it ſelf.</item>
               <item>Secondly, of the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> which is to be deſtroyed.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, Of the <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> with the Way or Manner of the deſtroying the one, and ſetting up of the other.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, Of the <hi>Time</hi> that it is to be begun, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, Before <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal comming.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, That it muſt be before the <hi>Call of the Jewes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Thirdly, That it is already begun, and hath taken place in this Nation, and that <hi>Cromwell</hi> with the <hi>Army,</hi> have Apoſtatized from that <hi>Work,</hi> and all the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> that have been up in this Nation ſince that time, have been, and ſtill are upon the foundation of the Apoſtacy.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To the firſt, to wit, of the <hi>fifth Kingdom</hi> it ſelf; I ſhall lay down this general Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, <hi>That there is an outward viſible Kingdom of the Father, which is given to Chriſt the Son, and is to take place over the whole world.</hi> Some of the Scriptures upon which my ſatisfaction is grounded in this truth are, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Thy Kingdom come,</hi> which word muſt needs be underſtood of this viſible Kingdom. Firſt, from the words that are joyned to it, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Will</hi> of God <hi>might be done in Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> which cannot ſo be till that <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> be ſet up over the <hi>Kingdoms of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This word <hi>Thy Kingdom come, &amp;c.</hi> cannot be meant of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential Kingdom mentioned <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.25. that having been in the world from the beginning: Neither can it be underſtood of the Kingdom of the <hi>Goſpel of Grace,</hi> becauſe it is a Prayer to be made even whileſt that <hi>Kingdom</hi> is in being: Neither can it be reſtrained to the <hi>Spirituall Kingdom</hi> that is within the Saints, becauſe thoſe that truly pray this Prayer (being Children) do already injoy that <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Neither can it be reſtrained to the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven</hi> in the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat Glory, becauſe that is not to come to the Saints, but they are to go or be taken up to it: therefore ſeeing it cannot be taken in either of theſe four ſences, and there being no other <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> that I read of, but the forementioned viſible <hi>Kingdom,</hi> this word muſt be referred to it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Scripture is <hi>Luke</hi> 21.31. <hi>When you ſee theſe things come to paſſe, Know ye that the Kingdom of God is nigh at hand.</hi> By <hi>theſe things,</hi> is meant the Signs of the latter day, or of Chriſts ſecond comming; and this <hi>Kingdom</hi> being
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192321:3"/>
nigh at hand, when the latter day ſignes are upon us, muſt needs be underſtood of this <hi>fifth Kingdom,</hi> which they have ſpecial relation to, and is known to be nigh at hand by them.</p>
            <p>The third Scripture is <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. <hi>And in the dayes of thoſe Kings, ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdom, &amp;c.</hi> This compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.14. muſt be underſtood of this viſible <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Scripture is <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. <hi>And the greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven, ſhall be given to the people of the Saints of the Moſt High,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him.</hi> This compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of our Lord,</hi> &amp;c. muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to this viſible Kingdom, which hath the Authority, Power, and Rule, in and over the whole World.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is called the <hi>Fathers Kingdom,</hi> as it is Originally from him who is the Creator, Former, and Diſpoſer of all things.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, As he doth in a ſpecial Manner erect or ſet up this <hi>Kingdom, The God of Heaven ſhall ſet it up,</hi> Dan. 2.44.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. As he is the Donor or Giver of it to the <hi>Son, Luke</hi> 1.32. <hi>The Lord God ſhall give him the Throne,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Kingdom alſo belongs to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Son.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As he is the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and ſo the true <hi>Heir, Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As he is, <hi>the Son of Man,</hi> the true <hi>Son of</hi> David, <hi>the ſeed of</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As he is the Son of Man, <hi>John</hi> 5.27. <hi>He hath Authority to execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe he is the Son of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As he is the true Son of <hi>David, Luke</hi> 1.32.69. <hi>The Lord God ſhall give him the Throne of his Father</hi> David. ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30. <hi>Of the Fruit of his Loynes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh, God hath ſworn with an Oath, that he would raiſe up Chriſt to ſit on his Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As he is the <hi>Seed of Abraham,</hi> Gen. 22.17, 18. <hi>Thy Seed ſhall poſſeſs the Gate of his Enemies;</hi> By <hi>Seed</hi> is meant <hi>Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.16. and by <hi>poſſeſſing the Gate,</hi> is to be underſtood, of poſſeſſing the Government, and execution of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10.12.15. <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.16.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is Chriſts Right by <hi>Promiſe, Iſa.</hi> 9.7. and by <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Oath, Pſa.</hi> 89.28, 29.34, 35, 36. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30. and by the Anointing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89.27.20. And by peculiar choyſe, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89.19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.1. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.18. And by Decree, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is Chriſts by the free gift of the Father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>I will give thee the Heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the Earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi> Luke 1.32. <hi>The Lord God ſhall give unto him the Throne,</hi> &amp;c. Dan. 7.14. <hi>There was given him Dominion,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 28.18. <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is Chriſts by deſert and purchaſe upon the account of his ſuffering, Rev. 5.12.13. <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain, to receive Power,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 53.12. <hi>Becauſe he hath poured out his ſoul unto death,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Lord will divide him a portion with the Great, and he ſhall divide the ſpoyl with the ſtrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192321:4"/>Sixthly, It is Chriſts in anſwer to the Great end of Creation <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. <hi>All things were created for him.</hi> ſo Pſal. 8.6. Compare <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8, The <hi>World to come</hi> is put in ſubjection to Chriſt as may appear from Verſe the 5th. This <hi>World to come,</hi> muſt needs be underſtood of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> which belongs unto, and is put under Chriſt the Son, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.21, 22. <hi>This world to come</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood of the Ultimate Glory in Heaven, becauſe that State is not to be put <hi>under</hi> Chriſt as the Son, but, as Son, he himſelf muſt become ſubject in it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. But this <hi>World to come,</hi> is noted in an eſpeciall manner to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſts Feet, and this is that State, or <hi>World to come,</hi> in which there ſhall be <hi>forgiveneſs,</hi> or <hi>blotting out of ſin,</hi> as is clearly implyed from <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.32. which compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. <hi>That your ſins may be blotted out when the time of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, and he ſhall ſend</hi> Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth clearly demonſtrate <hi>the World to come,</hi> to be this <hi>fifth Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is and ſhall be Chriſts by Conqueſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. <hi>The Lamb ſhall overcome them,</hi> &amp;c. Comp. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.2. and upon theſe grounds, this <hi>fifth King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> being Chriſts he is called <hi>King of Nations,</hi> Jer. 10.7. <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> Iſa. 9.6. <hi>And the Prince of the Kings of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 1.5. <hi>And King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> Rev. 17.14. Chap. 19.16. <hi>The bleſſed and only Potentate,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.15. with divers ſuch like Titles, which in the Scriptures of truth are given to him.</p>
            <p>The next thing that I would ſpeak to is, <hi>That this fifth Kingdom is outward and viſible, as well as glorious and ſpiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, From the time and manner of its riſing, mentioned <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34. <hi>Thou ſaweſt till that a Stone was cut out,</hi> &amp;c. If it were only ſpiritual, it might have been ſeen as well before the <hi>Image</hi> was, as after, but the <hi>Stone,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> doth not appear till after the <hi>Image</hi> is ſeen, and then appears as viſible as the <hi>Image,</hi> which <hi>Image</hi> holdeth forth the <hi>four</hi> great <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> or <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the World which have been and are viſible in their times. Now the <hi>Stone,</hi> being as viſible as the <hi>Image,</hi> and not ſeen till ſome time after the <hi>Image</hi> was ſeen, it muſt needs be a viſible <hi>Kingdom</hi> and not the ſpiritual and inviſible <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which was in being long before the Image appeared.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It muſt be outward and viſible if we conſider the work that this <hi>Kingdom</hi> is to do, it <hi>ſmites</hi> and <hi>breaks</hi> the <hi>Image,</hi> Dan. 2.34.44. which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with other Scriptures will appear to be an outward viſible breaking, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18.26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14, <hi>The ten Hornes,</hi> or <hi>ten Toes makes war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall overcome them.</hi> Now, if the Work be an outward and viſible ſmiting, the <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt needs be viſible alſo.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Dominion</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> is taken from &amp; filleth up the room of the <hi>fourth Kingdom,</hi> Dan. 2.35. <hi>The Stone became a great Mountain, and filled the whole Earth,</hi> ſo Dan. 7.17, 18. The <hi>four Beaſts</hi> are <hi>four Kings,</hi> which are the four great Monarchies, <hi>but the Saints ſhall take the Kingdom,</hi> See verſe 26. <hi>they ſhall take away his Dominion,</hi> &amp; in verſe 27. <hi>The Kingdom under the whole Heaven ſhall be given to the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Now the <hi>fourth Kingdom</hi> being viſible, this <hi>fifth Kingdom</hi> that fills up the room of the fourth muſt needs be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192321:4"/>Fourthly, The <hi>Throne</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> is the <hi>Throne of David,</hi> Luke 1.32. which is an outward viſible Throne; and in <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. there are two Thrones mentioned, one is called, the <hi>Fathers Throne,</hi> being rhe Throne where Chriſt now is, the other Chriſt calls his own <hi>Throne,</hi> which is the <hi>Throne of his Father Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> wherefore the Throne being viſible, the Kingdom muſt likewiſe be viſible.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The <hi>Lawes, Government,</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> under <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are outward and viſible, and take place upon the Bodies, Lives, Liberties and Eſtates of men, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.26. the Scriptures which are outward and viſible, are the Lawes, which God the only <hi>Law-giver (Iſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>James</hi> 4.12.) hath left, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.16. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Eſther</hi> 3.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7, 8. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18.19.20. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.12. The viſible <hi>Saints</hi> are to be the viſible <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> under <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King, Pſa.</hi> 45.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 32. 1. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 49.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18.22.27. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26.27. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.4.6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21. Theſe things being viſible the Kingdom muſt needs be viſible alſo; and thus much to the firſt particular of the <hi>fifth Kingdom</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Second thing which I propounded to ſpeak to, is the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> and in the entering upon that, Conſider in the firſt place the <hi>Image</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.31, 32. which <hi>Image</hi> doth comprehend and hold forth the four great Monarchies, which were to take place and have their time in the world, and they are deſcribed in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.3. by <hi>four great Beaſts,</hi> and the three laſt of theſe four Monarchies are deſcribed in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. the firſt by a <hi>Ram,</hi> the Second by a <hi>Hee-Goate,</hi> the laſt, which is the fourth Monarchy, by a <hi>little Horn,</hi> which are alſo ſpoken of <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe four Monarchies was that of the <hi>Chaldees, Dan.</hi> 2.38. He was that <hi>Head of Gold,</hi> and had his beginning as a part of the <hi>Image</hi> about the year 3362 from the Creation, and continued till about the year 3422, in all about 60 years.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Monarchy was that of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.32. is the <hi>Breaſt and Arms of Silver,</hi> and took place of the <hi>Chaldees, Dan.</hi> 5.30, 31. and continued till about the year 3620, in all about 198 years.</p>
            <p>The third Monarchy was that of the <hi>Graecians,</hi> which <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.32. is ſet forth by the <hi>Belly and Thighs of Braſſe,</hi> and in <hi>Dan,</hi> 8 21. by the <hi>rough Goate,</hi> which is there called, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Graecia,</hi> and ſucceeds the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which is ſet forth by the <hi>Ram</hi> with <hi>two Horns,</hi> verſe 20. This Monarchy of the <hi>Graecians,</hi> continued till about the year 3902 in all about 282 years.</p>
            <p>The fourth Monarchy was that of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.33. is ſet forth by the <hi>Leggs of Iron,</hi> and <hi>Feet part of Iron and part of Clay;</hi> and by the <hi>little Horn,</hi> (in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.9.11.12.) which <hi>takes away the daily ſacrifice, and caſts down the truth,</hi> And by the <hi>vild perſon</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.21. which in verſe 31. <hi>takes away the daily ſacrifice,</hi> and ſets up <hi>the abomination that maketh deſolate;</hi> This Monarchy took place as part of the <hi>Image</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. about forty two years before the Birth of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and was divided into two parts, which I underſtand to be held forth by the two <hi>Leggs of the Image,</hi> and continued in its <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh</hi> State till about 360 years after Chriſt before it was interrupted by and mixed with the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192321:5"/>To the firſt three <hi>Monarchies</hi> and the firſt part of the fourth I ſhall ſay little, but ſpecially inſiſt upon the Latter part of the fourth or <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy it being the laſt part of the <hi>Image,</hi> and the onely part which doth at this day remain in the world.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is evident that the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> is of two ſorts, the firſt is held forth by the <hi>Leggs of Iron;</hi> The ſecond by the <hi>feet,</hi> and <hi>toes</hi> of <hi>Iron and clay, Daniel</hi> 2.33. and in <hi>Daniel</hi> 7. The firſt part of it is held forth by the <hi>fourth Beaſt</hi> with the <hi>ten Horns</hi> and the other by the <hi>little Horn;</hi> In <hi>Revel.</hi> 12, 3. The firſt part of the <hi>Monarchy</hi> is held forth by the <hi>Red Dragon</hi> with <hi>ſeven heads and ten Horns,</hi> and <hi>ſeven Crownes upon his heads;</hi> The ſecond part in <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.1. is held forth by a <hi>Beaſt that riſeth out of the Sea.</hi> with <hi>ſeven Heads and ten Horns, and upon his Horns ten Crownes</hi> and as in verſe the fifth, <hi>is to continue forty and two Moneths.</hi> By the <hi>ten Horns</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>ten Kings</hi> or <hi>Kingdoms</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> which had their dependance upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and are called in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Ten Kings</hi> and ſo in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. And by the <hi>ſeven Heads</hi> I underſtand the ſeven Provinces that had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and before the riſe of the <hi>Antichriſtian ſtate,</hi> the <hi>Crowns</hi> or the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of the Government were upon the <hi>ſeven Heads</hi> or Provinces; And the <hi>Horns</hi> were as ſervants under the Emperour that had <hi>received no Kingdom</hi> till the <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſt</hi> came up <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.12. but at his coming up they <hi>receive power as Kings one hour with him,</hi> and then the <hi>Crowns</hi> are upon the <hi>Horns,</hi> and anſwers to <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.1. diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.3.</p>
            <p>The firſt part of this <hi>Romane</hi> ſtate was a lawful Power and to be obeyed as an <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> and the Lord Chriſt <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.27. payes <hi>Tribute</hi> to them, and Chap. 22.21. commands to <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith Rom. 13.1. <hi>the Powers that are,</hi> ſpeaking of them that were then in being <hi>are ordained of God,</hi> and giveth ſpecial charge to the Saints to obey them, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.1. And the Spirit of the Lord in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> foreſeeing that the <hi>Man of ſin</hi> would get up to the <hi>Throne,</hi> by ſpeaking <hi>evil of Dignities and deſpiſing Dominion</hi> as <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. Compare <hi>Jude</hi> 8. Rebelling againſt, yea caſting down the <hi>Civil Powers</hi> that ſo himſelf might obtain the <hi>Throne</hi> to Reign both over <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> which he did at length accompliſh, the Spirit (I ſay) foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, doth forewarn the Saints and charge them to be obedient to <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> with many cautions and Exhortations which ſtand in force to all true Magiſtrates to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of this <hi>Roman State</hi> is from <hi>Sathan,</hi> and riſeth out of of the <hi>Bottomleſſe Pit,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. Chap. 17.8. and is <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a great ſin to own it as the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> it being wicked and ſinful not onely in its Reign or exerciſe of Power, but in its very <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>Foundation,</hi> and to own it as <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> would be to charge him as the Author of ſin, and to ſet up <hi>the Man of ſin, and Myſtery of iniquity</hi> as Gods Ordinance, and thoſe that ſo do may be found equally guilty with thoſe that at this day cry up the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> as the Ordinance and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all that will not allow them this and therein fall down to them are charged as being
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192321:5"/>
againſt <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> but many will now grant that the <hi>Antichriſtian Miniſtry</hi> are ſinful, and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> both in their <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>Foundation,</hi> and to own them as the <hi>Miniſtry of Chriſt</hi> would be a very great evil, and why not the ſame in the <hi>Antichriſtian Magiſtracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Aſſertion that I ſhall lay down in this particular about the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> is, <hi>That there is an Antichriſtian Beaſt, or a wicked Power that riſeth out of the Bottomleſs pit, and is permitted by the Lord to take place in the world in the latter part of the Image Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Beaſt,</hi> is deſcribed <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.5. by a <hi>Little Horn,</hi> and in verſe the 11. it is called the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> This <hi>Horn</hi> or <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the laſt part of the <hi>Image Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and that which is to be <hi>taken away</hi> and deſtroyed by the <hi>Saints,</hi> after the <hi>judgement ſits</hi> as in verſe 26; and in verſe 24. <hi>another ſhall ariſe</hi> after the <hi>ten Horns</hi> in the firſt or <hi>Pagan State</hi> withour the <hi>Crowns</hi> as <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.3. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there are but three of the <hi>Horns</hi> or <hi>Kings</hi> ſubdued or brought down by the force and Power of this <hi>Little Horn,</hi> yet by the fair words, flattery and great proffers made by him to the reſt of them (to wit) that he would <hi>Crown and make them free ſtates if they will ſtand by him,</hi> they all at laſt fall in <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Power as Kings one hour with him,</hi> Revel. 17.12. and ſo this <hi>Horn</hi> or laſt <hi>Beaſt</hi> comes to have the <hi>ten Horns</hi> upon him with the <hi>Crowns</hi> upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This laſt part of the <hi>Roman State,</hi> mentioned Rev. 17.8. &amp; chap. 11.7. is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by a <hi>Beaſt</hi> that aſcendeth <hi>out of the bottomleſs pit,</hi> and is the ſame with the <hi>Little Horn before mentioned,</hi> and is diſtinguiſhed from the firſt <hi>part of the Roman State, Firſt</hi> in its <hi>Riſe,</hi> it comes from <hi>the Bottomleſs pit; Secondly</hi> by his carrying the <hi>Whore</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian Church, Rev.</hi> 17.3.7. <hi>Thirdly</hi> by the time of his <hi>Reign</hi> which is <hi>forty and two Moneths,</hi> and agrees with the time of the <hi>witneſſes prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying in ſackcloth, Revel.</hi> 11.3. and with the time of the <hi>Woman</hi> or <hi>Churches</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>in the wilderneſs, Rev.</hi> 12.6; <hi>Fourthly,</hi> by the <hi>Crowns</hi> being upon his <hi>Horns,</hi> which in the Firſt <hi>State</hi> were upon the <hi>Heads</hi> compare <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.1. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Fifthly</hi> by his <hi>Horns</hi> making <hi>War with the Lamb and being overcome by him, Revel.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Laſtly</hi> by his going into perdition, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.14.8.</p>
            <p>That this <hi>Beaſt</hi> which <hi>Aſcends from the bottomleſs pit</hi> is the ſame with the <hi>Little Horn</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. conſider, <hi>Firſt,</hi> this <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the laſt part of the <hi>Image Government</hi> and ſo is the <hi>Horn; Secondly</hi> this <hi>Beaſt</hi> ſets himſelf againſt God in <hi>great words and blaſphemy,</hi> ſo doth the <hi>Horn,</hi> Revel. 13.6. Compare with <hi>Dan..</hi> 20.25. <hi>Thirdly</hi> this <hi>Beaſt</hi> hath Power to make <hi>War with the Saints</hi> and for a time to <hi>overcome them,</hi> ſo hath the <hi>Horn,</hi> Revel. 13.7. Compare with <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.21.25. <hi>Fourthly</hi> this <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Horns</hi> are overcome and have their Power taken away by the <hi>Lamb</hi> and <hi>they that are on his ſide,</hi> which muſt be the <hi>Lamb</hi> by his Spirit in the Saints (for it cannot be thought that if the <hi>ten Horns</hi> ſhould be in being when Chriſt comes in perſon, they ſhould be able to begin or make <hi>War</hi> with him) the <hi>Saints</hi> do alſo <hi>take away to deſtroy and conſume,</hi> the Power of the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> Revel. 17.14. Compare Dan. 7.26.3. Fifthly this <hi>Beaſt goeth into perditon,</hi> or to <hi>Hell,</hi> So the <hi>Horn is given to the burning flame,</hi> Rev. 17.8. Compare with Dan. 7.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> this <hi>Beaſt</hi> or <hi>Horn</hi> before mentioned, is deſcribed in Dan. 2.41. by the <hi>Feet and Toes of the Image</hi> which appears to be the ſame with the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192321:6"/>
               <hi>Horn, Firſt</hi> as it is the laſt part of the <hi>Image Government; Secondly</hi> the <hi>Toes</hi> agrees with the <hi>Horns</hi> of this <hi>Beaſt</hi> in Revel. 17.12. <hi>Thirdly</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> or <hi>Horn,</hi> is deſtroyed by <hi>the Saints</hi> or by Chriſt in them; The <hi>feet</hi> and <hi>toes</hi> of the <hi>Image</hi> are ſmitten and broken by the <hi>ſtone,</hi> Dan. 2.34. which <hi>ſtone</hi> muſt either be the <hi>world</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi> in perſon, or <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his Spirit in his Saints; It cannot be meant of the <hi>world,</hi> firſt, becauſe it is the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that in a peculiar manner is ſet up by the <hi>God of Heaven</hi> as in verſe 44. <hi>Secondly</hi> becauſe it <hi>breaks</hi> down the worldly Government and <hi>fills the whole Earth,</hi> 3ly. Becauſe it is <hi>cut out without hands,</hi> (to wit) without worldly Powers, or the might of Man; In the next place, it cannot be Chriſt in Perſon, Firſt becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not <hi>cut out of the mountain,</hi> whether the <hi>mountain</hi> be underſtood of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>world,</hi> for it muſt be one of them; <hi>Secondly</hi> the <hi>Stone</hi> doth the <hi>work</hi> gradually, but <hi>Chriſts</hi> coming will be on a ſuddain as the <hi>Lightning</hi> that will effect his <hi>work</hi> at once; <hi>Thirdly</hi> Chriſt is no where called a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> But this <hi>ſtone</hi> is ſo called verſ. 44. <hi>Fourthly</hi> this <hi>ſtone</hi> is not <hi>cut out</hi> or ſeen till the laſt part of the <hi>Image Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> appears, <hi>thou ſaweſt till that a ſtone was cut out</hi> verſe 34. But if <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Perſon were <hi>cut out of the mountain,</hi> it muſt be long before the <hi>feet</hi> of the <hi>Image</hi> was in being, now ſeeing this <hi>ſtone</hi> cannot be underſtood of the <hi>world,</hi> or of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Perſon, it muſt needs be <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his Spirit in the <hi>Saints</hi> which Zech. 12.3. are called a <hi>Burthenſome ſtone,</hi> and ſo is the ſame with the <hi>Saints</hi> that deſtroy the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>Little Horn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, This <hi>Horn, Beaſt,</hi> or <hi>feet of the Image, is the</hi> ſame with that <hi>Man of ſin, Son of perdition, Myſtery of iniquity,</hi> and <hi>that Wicked</hi> mentioned 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.7.8. Firſt this <hi>man of ſin</hi> agrees with <hi>Antichriſt</hi> or the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in its riſe, the <hi>Beaſt</hi> riſeth through the change of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> from its <hi>Pagan State</hi> or rather through the ruine of it as <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. <hi>The Dragon gave him his Power,</hi> &amp;c. By the <hi>Dragon</hi> I underſtand the <hi>Devil,</hi> who Reigned by his Spirit in the wicked <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperours, who though their <hi>Authority</hi> was an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.2. yet they were ſwayed by the <hi>Devil</hi> to abuſe their <hi>Power</hi> and turn it againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>faithful followers;</hi> a Cloud of witneſſes to this, we have from the <hi>ten</hi> firſt <hi>Perſecutions</hi> carryed on by the <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperours, in which the <hi>Devil</hi> did appear like a <hi>Dragon,</hi> but when <hi>Antichriſt</hi> comes up, the <hi>Devil</hi> or <hi>Dragon</hi> quits his hold of the <hi>Pagan</hi> State, having a more ſubtile way to carry on his work under a pretence of Chriſtianity by this laſt <hi>Beaſt,</hi> he readily gives to this <hi>Beaſt</hi> his <hi>Power, Seat,</hi> and <hi>great Authority,</hi> and upon this the <hi>Pagan State</hi> falls, and therein <hi>him that did let,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.7. was removed <hi>out of the way, and</hi> ſo <hi>the wicked</hi> comes to be <hi>revealed</hi> or made viſible to be <hi>the Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>the wicked,</hi> or <hi>Man of ſin</hi> agrees in their <hi>Reign,</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Power,</hi> both ſetting themſelves againſt <hi>God,</hi> appearing with <hi>Power, Signes,</hi> and <hi>Lying Wonders,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.4.9.10. comp. Rev. 13.5, 6.13.14. alſo with <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this <hi>Man of Sin</hi> is the laſt <hi>Power</hi> upon Earth that precedes the <hi>coming,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his mouth and deſtroy with the brightneſs of his comming,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.8. <hi>By the Spirit of his Mouth,</hi> I underſtand the <hi>Anointing,</hi> which being given down thorough the word of the Lord upon the Saints, is called, <hi>the Spirit of his Mouth,</hi> by which the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192321:6"/>
               <hi>Antichriſtian Power is to be conſumed,</hi> and ſo agrees with the breaking work of the <hi>Stone</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. and with the <hi>Saints</hi> taking <hi>away</hi> and <hi>conſuming</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>little Horn</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. and that the <hi>Feet of the Image,</hi> the <hi>little Horn,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that comes from the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit</hi> are the laſt part of the <hi>Image Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and ſtands next to <hi>Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> hath been already cleared.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They agree in their ruine or deſtruction, as to <hi>Time, Inſtruments,</hi> and the <hi>Place</hi> into which they are <hi>Caſt;</hi> this <hi>man of ſin,</hi> is called the <hi>Son of Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which doth not only denote his helliſh <hi>Riſe,</hi> and <hi>Reign,</hi> but alſo that he muſt <hi>go into Perdition</hi> or <hi>Hell,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> alſo goeth into <hi>Perdition,</hi> or <hi>Hell,</hi> The <hi>man of ſin</hi> or <hi>Little Horn</hi> is alſo <hi>given to the burning flame,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.3. Comp. with Rev. 17.8. and Dan. 7.11. That they agree as to <hi>time</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments</hi> hath been already ſhewed, in theſe and ſeveral other particulars (which for brevity ſake I ſhall not inſiſt upon) Thus the <hi>feet</hi> and <hi>toes</hi> of the <hi>Image</hi> Dan. 2. The <hi>Little Horn,</hi> Dan. 7. The <hi>Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 17. The <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> 2 The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. do agree and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be one and the ſame though given under various <hi>Names,</hi> and <hi>Titles,</hi> and the comparing of them may through the bleſſing of the Lord help to a very full and clear deſcription of <hi>the Antichriſt</hi> that was to come and take place in the world in the <hi>latter day;</hi> onely this is to be noted, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> in deſcribing <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in the four forementioned places, doth ſometimes inſiſt chiefly upon the <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Beaſtly Power,</hi> and ſometime doth take in and inſiſt upon both the <hi>Civil,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>falſe Church</hi> part as they are twiſted together; As in the <hi>feet</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> and <hi>the Man of Sin revealed,</hi> when he who <hi>did let ſhould be taken out of the way,</hi> but I ſhall ſpeak more to that in the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall lay down and endeavour to clear is, <hi>That the Antichriſt, or laſt part of the Image Government doth conſiſt, or is made up of two ſorts, to wit, Civil and Eccleſiaſticall, both twiſted or mixed together, the Magiſterial, or Civil Government being united to and involved in the Eccleſiaſtical or falſe Church State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This appears, Firſt, From the <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes of the Image</hi> that are of <hi>Iron mixed with Clay,</hi> Dan. 2.41. by the <hi>Iron</hi> I underſtand the <hi>Civil State</hi> as <hi>Verſe</hi> 33. The <hi>Roman Power</hi> in its <hi>Civil Sate,</hi> is ſet forth by <hi>Iron Leggs;</hi> and by <hi>Clay,</hi> I underſtand the <hi>earthy falſe Church,</hi> which is ſet forth by a <hi>Beaſt coming up out of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 13.11. <hi>The Civil Power</hi> eſpouſing and joyning in affinity with the <hi>Whore,</hi> ſhe being not of <hi>God</hi> but brought forth by <hi>Man,</hi> or rather by the <hi>Devil</hi> in man, is called <hi>the ſeed of Men,</hi> Dan. 2.43. This Eſpouſal, or joyning in affinity, I underſtand to be the mingling with the <hi>ſeed of Men,</hi> and by this ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>Imperial Power</hi> was not ſtrengthned, but indeed weakened, as <hi>Verſe</hi> 42. The <hi>falſe Church</hi> may alſo upon ſeveral other accounts, be fitly ſet forth by <hi>Clay,</hi> as in its <hi>Riſe, Brittleneſs, Foulneſs,</hi> and its <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>cleaving</hi> or <hi>ſticking</hi> to other things that comes nigh unto it.</p>
            <p>This may appear, Secondly, From the <hi>revealing of the wicked,</hi> by removing of <hi>him</hi> that did <hi>let</hi> (which was as I underſtand the <hi>Roman Emperour</hi>) out of the way, 2 Theſ. 2.7.8. <hi>Him that did let,</hi> muſt either be <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Devil,</hi> or <hi>Man,</hi> It could not be God, becauſe, <hi>him that did let,</hi> was to be removed <hi>out of the way,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:192321:7"/>
which would be blaſphemy in any to refer to God. Secondly, It could not be the Devil, for he <hi>that did let,</hi> appears to ſtand in the way to hinder the <hi>Devils King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> taking place, which would be <hi>Satan</hi> againſt <hi>Satan,</hi> or <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf,</hi> Mark 3.23.24.26. and if it can be neither <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Satan,</hi> then it muſt be <hi>Man,</hi> and can be referred to no other <hi>Man</hi> but the <hi>Roman Emperour</hi> who in the exerciſe of his <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſh Power,</hi> did for ſome hundreds of years after <hi>Pauls</hi> dayes hinder the <hi>Myſtery of iniquity</hi> appearing in the <hi>falſe Church</hi> from coming to his deſired <hi>Throne;</hi> The <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> grew very high and ſought long to get the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>Civil Judicatory</hi> over the <hi>State,</hi> as they had over the <hi>Church,</hi> but they could not obtain the <hi>Throne,</hi> till the <hi>Emperour</hi> was brought down to their foot and (as to his <hi>Imperial Power</hi>) was taken out of the way, and when this was effected <hi>Antichriſt</hi> aſſumed the <hi>Throne,</hi> and ſo <hi>the wicked</hi> came to <hi>be revealed;</hi> who though he had the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Seat</hi> before, yet was not ſo revealed to be <hi>that wicked</hi> mentioned 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. till he got the <hi>Civil Seat</hi> alſo, and this doth further clear, that <hi>the wicked Antichriſt</hi> in his Throne muſt be made up of <hi>Civil,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This may further appear by the two <hi>Beaſts</hi> mentioned, Revel. 13. the firſt comes out of <hi>the Sea,</hi> verſe 1. which I underſtand to be the <hi>Civil Roman Power</hi> in its laſt <hi>State</hi> that riſeth by the <hi>Rebellions,</hi> and <hi>Sea-like</hi> rageing tumults of the people, being encouraged and promoted by <hi>Sathan</hi> in the <hi>falſe Church,</hi> (though not yet mounted upon the <hi>Beaſt;</hi>) By theſe <hi>tumults,</hi> the <hi>Roman Power,</hi> in its <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> and firſt <hi>State</hi> (that was very glorious before) comes to be waſted and at laſt deſtroyed, and ſo the <hi>Power</hi> brought under the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that comes out of <hi>the Sea,</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> or <hi>Dragon,</hi> being very willing to make a change of the <hi>Power</hi> from the <hi>Pagan State,</hi> that he might Mount the <hi>Whore</hi> readily gives <hi>his Power, Seat, and great Authority to this Beaſt.</hi> The <hi>Second Beaſt</hi> is mentioned in verſe the 11. of this 13. Chapter and deſcribed as coming up out of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and in verſe 12. is ſaid to <hi>exerciſe all the Power of the Firſt Beaſt</hi> (to wit the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that comes out of the Sea) and verſ. 13.14. doth <hi>great Wonders,</hi> and worketh <hi>Miracles</hi> before him, &amp;c. and is called the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> Revel. 19.20. This <hi>Beaſt</hi> muſt be underſtood of the <hi>falſe Church</hi> which cometh not from <hi>Heaven</hi> as doth the <hi>true Church,</hi> but from <hi>Earth</hi> or <hi>Hell,</hi> and in his firſt appearance his <hi>Horns</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> are like a <hi>Lamb</hi> verſe 11. or like <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for ſo this <hi>falſe Church</hi> would be accounted, but his words are like the devil, <hi>he ſpake as a Dragon</hi> verſe 11; and this <hi>falſe Church</hi> joyning her ſelf to, and riding upon the <hi>Beaſt</hi> comes to ſway or exerciſe the <hi>Civil Power,</hi> and ſo is ſaid verſ. 12. to <hi>exerciſe all the Power of the firſt Beast,</hi> not that the <hi>firſt Beaſt is</hi> deſtroyed, for this <hi>Whore</hi> cauſeth him to be worſhipped and doth great things before him v. 12. 14. Since the <hi>falſe Church</hi> hath been mixed with, and mounted upon the <hi>civil Power,</hi> (for her own ends,) ſhe cryes up this wicked <hi>Beast,</hi> as the Ordinance of God, though in truth it comes from the <hi>Devil,</hi> yea and ſhe can bring Scripture (though abuſed and wreſted) as the <hi>Devil</hi> did to <hi>Christ,</hi> and cryes up obedience to it, condemning all that will not fall down to the <hi>Beast,</hi> as being thoſe that <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey Magistrates, deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> which Scriptures indeed were ſpoken of, and much fulfilled by this <hi>falſe Church</hi> till this <hi>Beast</hi> on which ſhe rides came up.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:192321:7"/>
            <p>Fourthly, The mixture of this <hi>Antichriſtian State</hi> may further appear by the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>VVhore</hi> mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. The <hi>Beaſt that was and is not and yet is,</hi> verſe 8. holds forth the <hi>Civil Power</hi> in its two fold <hi>State;</hi> Firſt, In its <hi>Pagan State,</hi> before the viſible riſe of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Secondly, In its <hi>Antichriſtian State,</hi> when it carries the <hi>VVhore;</hi> The <hi>Beast that was,</hi> which word <hi>was,</hi> reſpects him in the glory of the <hi>Pagan State,</hi> in which he was a <hi>Beast,</hi> and like a Beaſt rather then like a <hi>Man,</hi> he carried it in the <hi>ten</hi> firſt <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> and this word, <hi>Is not,</hi> reſpects him in his <hi>Antichristian State</hi> as carrying the <hi>VVhore,</hi> which was not in being in <hi>Johns</hi> daies who was the Penman of this word; And this word, <hi>and yet is,</hi> reſpects the <hi>Pagan State</hi> which was in being in <hi>Johns day;</hi> And this word <hi>ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſs pit,</hi> reſpects his <hi>Antichriſtian State</hi> which comes from <hi>Hell,</hi> and in this State, I underſtand he is called the <hi>eighth Head,</hi> ver. 11; The other <hi>Seven Heads</hi> being brought down for, and their Power divolved upon this <hi>Beast,</hi> he is called the <hi>eighth,</hi> and yet is ſaid to be of the <hi>Seventh,</hi> and the <hi>ten Horns</hi> ver. 12. receive Power as <hi>Kings one hour with him,</hi> being all thereby fitted for, and engaged to Mount the <hi>VVhore;</hi> The <hi>VVhore,</hi> ver. 1. holds forth the falſe Church, that would be counted the <hi>ſpouſe of Christ,</hi> but commits <hi>whoredom</hi> with <hi>Idolls,</hi> and <hi>fornication with the Kings of the earth,</hi> and is not built upon <hi>Christ</hi> as the <hi>foundation,</hi> But verſe 15. <hi>ſitteth upon peoples, and multitudes, and Nations, and Tongues,</hi> that being the ſtrength of the <hi>falſe Church,</hi> who by her <hi>ſorceries</hi> and <hi>VVhoredoms as the Mother of Harlots and Abominations of the earth,</hi> obtains the Power and <hi>Reigneth over the Kings of the earth.</hi> ver. 18.</p>
            <p>Fithly, This mixt <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Antichrist</hi> in the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power,</hi> is further held forth, by the <hi>Beaſt and falſe Prophet.</hi> Rev. 19.20, 21. which place ſpeaks of them in the laſt and finall ſtroke that comes upon them, for though the <hi>fifth Viall,</hi> Rev. 16.10. <hi>is poured out upon the Seat of the Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Judgment</hi> and fall of the <hi>Whore</hi> is ſet forth in Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. and begining of the 19th yet ſome Reliques of both the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>Whore</hi> remaining till very near or unto the perſonal Coming of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Devil having but a <hi>ſhort time</hi> to reign, gathers up all his forces and engageth the <hi>Kings of the Earth</hi> to come up with him againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> and then the laſt <hi>Viall</hi> comes upon them at <hi>Chriſts</hi> perſonal appearing and compleats their ruin and ſo both theſe parts of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> by this ſtroke are deſtroyed together, compare <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20, 21. with Chap. 16. Ver. 13, 14, 16, 17. Having ſpoken of this <hi>Beaſt and falſe Prophet</hi> held forth by the two <hi>Beaſts</hi> in Chap. 13. I ſhall ſpeak no more of them in this place.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If we conſult the Hiſtories and alſo what we have ſeen of the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an State</hi> in our day, it hath been made up of theſe two parts, <hi>viz. Civil</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical,</hi> which like <hi>Twins,</hi> have gone together in all their wickedneſs, one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the other and calling for obedience; The <hi>falſe Church</hi> and her <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> being propped up by the falſe <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> calls for and preaches up obedience to it as Gods ordinance, and they muſt be <hi>killed</hi> that will <hi>not worſhip the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.15. The <hi>falſe Magiſtracy</hi> doth the like for the <hi>falſe Church</hi> and her <hi>Ministery,</hi> crying them up as the <hi>true Church</hi> and <hi>Ministry of Christ,</hi> and all that will not fall down to this <hi>VVhore</hi> in paying of <hi>Tythes, Church-Rates,</hi> following her <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> and ſuch like abominations muſt be impriſoned, baniſhed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192321:8"/>
or <hi>killed,</hi> and thus the <hi>Beast</hi> bears, yea is ſaid to carry the <hi>VVhore,</hi> Rev. 17.7. and is the <hi>Whores</hi> drudge or ſlave to do her wicked ſervice; theſe two have been in conjunction in and are guilty of the <hi>blood of the Saints,</hi> and the ſeveral perſecutions, ſince <hi>Antichrist</hi> came to the Throne, have been on this wiſe carryed on, the <hi>Eccleſiastical Power</hi> have adjudged and condemned and ſo delivered over to the <hi>Civil Power,</hi> who have executed and killed them with much rage and greedineſs, and after a moſt cruel manner, and although the <hi>Civil Power</hi> would at this day when the Lord is comming to <hi>make inquiſition for blood,</hi> ſlip out their Necks and excuſe themſelves as if they were free and had done no wrong to, nor <hi>ſhed the blood of the Saints</hi> and may have many Advocates pleading at a high rate on their behalf, and ſaying that <hi>Judgment ſhall not fall upon them</hi> and further to evince this, do give them the title of Chriſtian <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and <hi>that many of them are good men,</hi> yet all this will not excuſe them from the ſtroke, when the Lord according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5, 6. comes to <hi>avenge the blood of his Saints and Prophets,</hi> and Pſal. 9.16. ſhall be <hi>known by the judgment which he executeth,</hi> for no doubt the guilt of much blood will be found in the skirts of the <hi>Civil Power</hi> and their <hi>ſin will find them out,</hi> and though <hi>good men</hi> be in the place of <hi>Power,</hi> it will not ſave from <hi>the Judgement,</hi> for <hi>Gods controverſie</hi> is not ſo much with the <hi>Perſons</hi> as with the <hi>Beastly Powers,</hi> and the title of <hi>Christian Magistrates</hi> will not excuſe, but rather condemne them as the <hi>Antichristian Power,</hi> and the <hi>Fountaines and Rivers of waters,</hi> upon which the <hi>third Viall</hi> comes, Rev. 16.4. doth not exclude but include this <hi>Civil Power;</hi> Having thus laid down my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the <hi>fifth Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> which ſhould be erected or ſet up in the latter day, &amp; of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Beast,</hi> which is to be deſtroyed; I ſhall now come to ſpeak to the third thing which is the great queſtion at this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſhall theſe things be brought forth? by what Instruments and in what way?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to this Queſtion, Firſt, this <hi>VVork</hi> belongs to God who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to accompliſh it. As firſt, the deſtroying the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> the beating <hi>down</hi> of Chriſts <hi>foes before him,</hi> making them <hi>his footſtool,</hi> clothing <hi>them with ſhame,</hi> and <hi>avenging</hi> the blood of the Saints upon <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> Pſal. 89.23. Pſa. 110.1. &amp; 132.18. Rev. 6.10. Chap. 19.2. Secondly, the ſetting up of the <hi>fifth Kingdom</hi> alſo belongs to God, Dan. 2.44. Pſal. 89, 27.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though God be the main <hi>Agent</hi> in this <hi>VVork</hi> yet he doth it by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,</hi> and the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> are his <hi>Saints,</hi> whom he will call to and anoint for this <hi>VVork,</hi> and ſo God is ſaid to do it becauſe it is done by his Spirit in the <hi>Saints</hi> whom he ſhall chooſe.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> in deſtroying the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> and ſo in ſetting up the <hi>fifth Kingdom</hi> which doth immediatly Succeed, Take the place, and Fill up the room of the <hi>fourth,</hi> conſider the following Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34. <hi>the Stone</hi> (which is the <hi>Saints,</hi> anointed for and called to the Work as I have before ſhewed) <hi>ſmites the Image on his feet,</hi> (which hath alſo been ſhewed to be the <hi>Antichriſtian State</hi>) and <hi>breaks</hi> them in pieces, So <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18. <hi>The Saints ſhall take the Kingdom;</hi> Now though the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is given to them by promiſe, and obtained for them by the Power of God, yet they are ſaid <hi>to take it,</hi> which muſt be underſtood of their being uſed as <hi>Inſtruments</hi> in taking
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192321:8"/>
the <hi>Power, Rule</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> from the <hi>Image,</hi> or that part of it which ſtands next before <hi>Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> which muſt be done by deſtroying, or breaking in pieces that part of the <hi>Image</hi> which is in being when this <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> comes to take place Dan. 7.26. <hi>They</hi> (that is the Saints whom he <hi>wears out</hi> verſe 25.) <hi>ſhall take away his,</hi> (that is the <hi>Little Horn</hi> verſ. 8. and 24. which have been already ſhewed to be the <hi>Antichristian State) Dominion</hi> (that is his <hi>Power, Rule,</hi> or <hi>Government) to conſume, and to deſtroy it unto the end.</hi> In <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.31. The <hi>Angel</hi> is ſpeaking of the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Fourth Kingdom,</hi> which took <hi>away, the dayly ſacrifice,</hi> and verſ. 32. ſaith, But <hi>the people that do know their God ſhall be ſtrong and do exploits;</hi> The <hi>people that do know their God,</hi> are the Saints, and by their being <hi>strong</hi> and doing <hi>exploits,</hi> I underſtand to be the ſervice that the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall do in the deſtroying this <hi>Fourth Kingdom,</hi> alſo <hi>Num.</hi> 24.14. <hi>I will advertiſe thee what this people ſhall do to thy people in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes,</hi> and <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.2. <hi>They ſhall take them captives,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41.14.15. <hi>Fear not thou worm</hi> Jacob (to wit the Saints in a low condition) <hi>I will make thee a new ſharp threſhing Inſtrument,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thou ſhalt threſh,</hi> (that is break in pieces or deſtroy) <hi>the mountains,</hi> (to wit the great <hi>worldly Powers Iſai.</hi> 2.2.) <hi>and beat them ſmall, and ſhall make the Hills,</hi> (which alſo intends the worldly Powers) <hi>as Chaff,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.2. <hi>Shake thy ſelf from the dust looſe thy ſelf from the bonds of thy neck O captive Daughter of Zion;</hi> by <hi>the bonds of thy neck,</hi> and <hi>the dust,</hi> I underſtand the <hi>Government,</hi> and wicked Tyranny, that <hi>Babylon</hi> hath had and exerciſed over <hi>Zion,</hi> and by <hi>ſhaking and looſing</hi> her <hi>ſelf,</hi> muſt needs be underſtood to be the breaking off, or deſtroying that <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and this muſt be done by <hi>Zion</hi> her ſelf, to wit, the People of God, Cha. 51.16. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> Cha. 50.45. Speaking of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſurely the least of the flock ſhall draw them out,</hi> by <hi>the Flock,</hi> is meant the People of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. and by <hi>draw them out,</hi> I underſtand the rewarding and deſtroying of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and this Scripture muſt be applyed to ſpiritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe it was not the <hi>Saints</hi> but the <hi>Medes</hi> that <hi>drew out</hi> litteral <hi>Babylon,</hi> as the ſame Chapter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. doth manifeſt; In <hi>Micha.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Zion</hi> (to wit the Lords Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) is fitted for and called to <hi>ariſe and threſh the Nations. Iſa.</hi> 13.3, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2.3. <hi>Job.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.7. So <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Zion</hi> muſt <hi>deliver</hi> her <hi>ſelf,</hi> and her <hi>ſons</hi> muſt be <hi>raiſed up against the ſons of Greece;</hi> Rev. 18.4.6. the peculiar People of God are commanded to <hi>reward Babylon,</hi> Rev. 15.6. and 16.1. the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> with the <hi>Viols comes out of the Temple;</hi> the <hi>Vials,</hi> do contain the <hi>ſeven last plagues,</hi> or the judgements of God that are to accompliſh the deſtruction of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and avenging the blood of the Saints; the <hi>Temple</hi> is the <hi>Church,</hi> or the Saints of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. and by the <hi>Angels,</hi> I underſtand thoſe Saints, that are <hi>choſen,</hi> and <hi>called</hi> of God as Miniſters or ſervants employed in that honourable work to <hi>execute</hi> his <hi>judgements;</hi> theſe with many other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do make it very evident, that the Saints or people of God, muſt be uſed by him in this great and glorious <hi>work;</hi> and the <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> taking place, and filling up the roome of the <hi>Fourth;</hi> Dan. 2.35. The <hi>Stone,</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom became a great mountain and filled the whole Earth.</hi> the like in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. it will appear from the Scriptures before mentioned that the Saints muſt be uſed both in the <hi>deſtroying,</hi> and <hi>building work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:192321:9"/>But I know it is further queried, <hi>How ſhall the Saints be uſed in this work, and by what meanes ſhall they accompliſh it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, I ſhall lay down theſe particulars;</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That they which ſhall be uſed in the work, muſt be ſuch whom the Lord ſhall chooſe, and call in to it.</hi> The <hi>Lambs</hi> Army <hi>are call'd and choſen,</hi> Rev. 17.14. It is not whom Man will chooſe, but whom the Lord ſhall chooſe: <hi>Samuel</hi> would have choſen <hi>Eliab,</hi> but he muſt not ſtand, becauſe God had refuſed him, and it was <hi>David</hi> that was Gods choſen. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. This hath been the evil of many in our dayes, to preſume to put themſelves and others upon the <hi>Lords VVork,</hi> Some becauſe they are men of <hi>great wit</hi> and <hi>parts;</hi> Others, becauſe they are men of <hi>great eſtates</hi> and <hi>high</hi> in the World; Others, becauſe they are tryed <hi>Souldiers, Men of valour and courage;</hi> yea, and many like <hi>Samuel,</hi> have been crying ſuch up as the Lords annointed, and have not firſt made diligent ſearch, whether the Lord had <hi>choſen</hi> them, and this hath proved like <hi>Uzzahs</hi> touching the <hi>Ark,</hi> they have ſtumbled, fallen, and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That <hi>the Inſtruments muſt not only be ſuch as are called and choſen,</hi> but ſuch as have received the <hi>annointing</hi> for the <hi>work:</hi> by which <hi>annointing,</hi> they are not only made <hi>faithful,</hi> but do obtain <hi>light</hi> in, and <hi>love</hi> unto it, with <hi>wiſdom, faith</hi> and <hi>courage</hi> for the managing of it. This <hi>work,</hi> though done by the <hi>Saints,</hi> muſt not be by their, or the <hi>might</hi> or <hi>power</hi> of men, but by this annointing, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.27. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 59.19. <hi>Haggai,</hi> 2.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.6. Being thus <hi>called, choſen,</hi> and <hi>annointed,</hi> they ſhall be uſed; Firſt, by <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>prayer,</hi> with <hi>praiſes,</hi> as <hi>Joſhua, Gideon,</hi> and divers others were in the <hi>Typical</hi> part of this <hi>work</hi> and how much more in the <hi>Anti-type,</hi> which doth farr exceed it in ſpirituality, ſhall the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> be ſo uſed; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Ask of me, and I will give thee.</hi> &amp;c. which muſt reſpect Chriſt as <hi>King</hi> in his members, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.30, 32, 33. <hi>Who through faith ſubdued Kingdomes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.15. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6. <hi>Let the high prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God be in their mouths,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.3.4.5. Secondly, by the <hi>word of their Teſtimony,</hi> which they bear for <hi>Chriſt</hi> againſt <hi>Antichriſt, Rev.</hi> 12.11, 17. Laſtly, by <hi>Material weapons,</hi> in a military way, Chriſt being the <hi>Captain General,</hi> and <hi>chief leader</hi> of this Army, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <hi>The Lamb ſhall overcome them, and they that are on his ſide, are called, choſen and faithful.</hi> Pſal. 110.3. <hi>In the day of the aſſembling of thy Army,</hi> (for ſo ſome read the words) <hi>Thy people</hi> (ſpeaking to Chriſt) <hi>ſhall be willing.</hi> This Pſalm doth in an eſpecial manner relate to the <hi>work of the later day.</hi> Rev. 19.14. <hi>The Armies followed</hi> Chriſt, which <hi>Armies</hi> muſt reſpect the <hi>Saints,</hi> as being them that <hi>are arrayed in fine linnen,</hi> Verſ. 8. That the Saints ſhall be uſed with material weapons, conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the <hi>War</hi> cannot be reſtrained to that ſpiritual <hi>War,</hi> mentioned 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. which <hi>war</hi> required ſpiritual weapons only, but this is an outward viſible <hi>war,</hi> as <hi>ſmiting,</hi> and <hi>breaking</hi> the viſible <hi>Image Government,</hi> taking away the viſible <hi>Power</hi> of the laſt <hi>Beaſt, Dan.</hi> 2. and Chapter the 7th. and a viſible <hi>overcoming,</hi> and breaking the <hi>Horns,</hi> or viſible <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Ten Kingdoms,</hi> that received their <hi>Power</hi> with the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> which <hi>Hornes</hi> do begin a viſible War with <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as it is owned, and carried on by his Saints, who are the <hi>Members</hi> of his Body, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192321:9"/>Secondly, That they ſhall be uſed with Material Weapons, may appear from <hi>Joel,</hi> 3.10. <hi>Beat your Plow-ſhares into ſwords, and your pruning-hooks into ſpears, let the weak ſay I am ſtrong.</hi> In which Scripture, I would note three things, Firſt, That it is a prophecy of the <hi>latter day work,</hi> when <hi>Multitudes</hi> ſhall appear in the <hi>valley of deciſion,</hi> which hath never yet been fulfilled, as is moſt evident, if the ſcope of the Propheſie be conſulted. Secondly, This 10th. Verſe is ſpoken to the Saints, or people of God, the ſcope of the words leads to the Saints, and the 11th. verſe is a Call to the <hi>Heathen,</hi> for God will gather the <hi>Heathen</hi> as well as his own people, to the <hi>valley of deciſion,</hi> according to <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8. and this word of encouragement, <hi>Let the weak ſay I am strong,</hi> is not ſpoken to the enemies of God, but is a bleſſed word for his own people, and by it the whole verſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be directed to them. Laſtly, the <hi>ſwords</hi> and <hi>ſpears</hi> are not <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> but <hi>material weapons,</hi> becauſe they are made of <hi>plow-ſhares</hi> and <hi>pruning-hooks,</hi> and are to be uſed in the Lords great <hi>Controverſie</hi> with the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and the enemies of his <hi>Church.</hi> This Truth may further appear, from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6, 7, 8. <hi>Let a two-edged ſword be in their hands, to execute vengeance,</hi> &amp;c. This Pſalm muſt alſo reſpect the <hi>latter day,</hi> when the <hi>meek ſhallbe beautified with ſalvation,</hi> ver. 4. and this propheſie hath never been fulfilled ſince this Pſalme was penned, but muſt be fulfilled in the execution of <hi>the judgement</hi> that is to come upon the World in this <hi>latter day;</hi> This muſt be a <hi>material ſword.</hi> Firſt, becauſe the <hi>work</hi> that the Saints are to do with it, is outward, viſible <hi>work,</hi> viz. <hi>to bind Kings and Nobles, and to execute the judgment written,</hi> verſ. 8.9. 2dly. This <hi>ſword</hi> is to be in <hi>their hands,</hi> and therefore muſt be a <hi>material ſword;</hi> if it were ſpiritual, it would be in their hearts, or in their mouths and included in the <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>praiſes</hi> before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of; this may further appear from <hi>Luke</hi> 22.36. <hi>He that hath no ſword, let him ſell his garment and buy one.</hi> That this Sword relates to the <hi>latter day,</hi> muſt needs be granted, becauſe it is ſpoken in the <hi>latter day;</hi> for the whole day from Chriſts coming into the fleſh, to the end of the world, is called the <hi>latter dayes</hi> or <hi>time, Acts</hi> 2.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. This <hi>latter day, or last times,</hi> muſt be conſidered under a two-fold diſpenſation, the one of Suffering, the other of Action. In the <hi>first,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> muſt be bound with <hi>chains,</hi> &amp; <hi>killed,</hi> and <hi>countted as ſheep for the ſlaughter,</hi> Rom. 8.36. comp. Luke 21.12, 16. And in the <hi>ſecond,</hi> the Saints ſhall <hi>bind with chaines, and take them captives, whoſe captives they were,</hi> Iſa. 14.2 comp. Pſal. 149. In the <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> or <hi>Little Horn</hi> ſhall <hi>wear out the Saints;</hi> In the <hi>ſecond,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall <hi>take away his Dominion,</hi> Dan. 7. In the <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> muſt Suffer in <hi>Babylon,</hi> under <hi>yokes</hi> and <hi>bonds,</hi> and ſo be hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the head; In the <hi>ſecond, Zion</hi> (or the Saints) muſt <hi>deliver her ſelf,</hi> and <hi>put on</hi> her <hi>Beautifull Garments,</hi> and <hi>lift up her head, and looſe her ſelf from the bands of her neck,</hi> or the Government of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that is upon her, <hi>and ſhake her ſelf from the dust.</hi> In the firſt, <hi>Babylon</hi> is exerciſing Cruelty, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny over the Saints, and they are patiently to bear it, and if they be ſmitten <hi>on the one cheek, they muſt turn the other, and if any man will ſue them at the Law, and take away their coat,</hi> (which muſt be whileſt the wicked <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> Law is in force) they muſt <hi>let him have</hi> their <hi>Cloak alſo:</hi> But in the <hi>Second,</hi> the Saints muſt <hi>render to Babylon double.</hi> Compare theſe following Scriptures <hi>Dan.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:192321:10"/>
7.25. with verſ. 26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. with Chap. 17.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.1.2. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.39.40. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6. This Scripture <hi>Luke</hi> 22.36. doth clearly hold forth this two-fold diſpenſation, for it cannot be applyed to the day when <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were upon the Earth, which was a day of ſuffering, wherein they were not to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> as <hi>Math.</hi> 5.39. with many other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to this purpoſe, both in the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and the <hi>Epiſtles;</hi> and Chriſt tells them at the ſame time, that <hi>two ſwords</hi> were <hi>enough,</hi> verſ. 38. and therefore could not be the time in which he that had <hi>no ſword,</hi> muſt <hi>ſell his garment and buy one,</hi> but holds forth another diſpenſation, in which the <hi>Saints</hi> muſt be called to <hi>Action</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the <hi>ſetting up</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and though the words were ſpoken to the <hi>diſciples</hi> that were then with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the ſuffering day, yet he delivers it to them as they repreſented the whole body of <hi>Goſpel</hi> Believers, that were, or ſhould come over to faith in him to the end of the world; and ſo the <hi>Ordinances, Rules,</hi> and <hi>Work</hi> that the Saints were to obſerve and do till <hi>Chriſts</hi> Second <hi>coming,</hi> are <hi>delivered</hi> unto, and <hi>received</hi> by the <hi>diſciples</hi> that were with him in that day; <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the opening the extent of his prayer, <hi>John.</hi> 17.20. cleares this, and alſo in his general exhortation, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.37. <hi>What I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo the diſciples received from Chriſt the <hi>work</hi> that is to be done by the Saints in this laſt part of the <hi>latter dayes.</hi> Much more might be urged to clear this matter, if it were expedient in this place; by all which it may appear, that there is a <hi>two-fold Diſpenſation</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel-day,</hi> and that this word of <hi>buying a ſword,</hi> muſt referre to the latter; this cannot be a <hi>Spiritual ſword,</hi> it being to be <hi>bought</hi> by <hi>ſelling</hi> of a <hi>garment;</hi> It was the errour of <hi>Sym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> the 8th. to think that the <hi>Gifts of the Spirit</hi> might be <hi>bought:</hi> and further, this muſt needs referre to a time when the <hi>Saints</hi> muſt uſe a <hi>Material ſword,</hi> becauſe they muſt rather want their <hi>garments</hi> (though very needful and uſeful) then want a <hi>ſword.</hi> The next Sc ipture that doth imply this truth is <hi>John</hi> 18.36. <hi>If my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were of this world, or from hence, Then would my ſervants fight that I ſhould not be delivered to the Jewes.</hi> This muſt needs be meant a fighting with <hi>material weapons,</hi> which ſhould reſcue <hi>Chriſt</hi> from the <hi>Jewes;</hi> and Chriſt ſpeaking of that time, ſaith, <hi>Now is my Kingdome not from hence;</hi> which words do imply, that there is a time when his <hi>Kingdome</hi> ſhall be from <hi>hence,</hi> and though it be a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and <hi>Glorious Kingdom,</hi> yet it ſhall be <hi>ſet up,</hi> in, and over the world, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. <hi>The dominion under the whole heaven ſhall be given</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The Kingdomes of this world are become,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo the <hi>Kingdome of Chriſt</hi> may be ſaid to be from <hi>hence,</hi> and when ſo it ſhall be, His ſervants will fight. The next Scripture that may clear this, is <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10. <hi>Curſed be he that withholdeth his ſword from blood.</hi> This word relates to a time when Gods <hi>judgments</hi> are to be executed upon his <hi>Enemies,</hi> and is ſpoken to the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> whom he will uſe, (as in the beginning of the verſe.) Now the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> that God will uſe in the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his <hi>Judgements</hi> in the <hi>latter day,</hi> I underſtand to be his <hi>Saints,</hi> as I have already ſhewed, and ſo this word is ſpoken to them, and proves that they muſt be imployed with <hi>material weapons;</hi> I ſhall not cite more ſcriptures to this, but ſpeak to ſome principal objections that are made againſt this truth <hi>of the Saints being uſed (with material weapons) in the deſtruction of Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192321:10"/>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>The Ten Hornes muſt hate the Whore, and burn her fleſh with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw,</hi> That the <hi>Ten Hornes</hi> ſhall be imployed in this work, none can deny that own the Authority of Scripture, but that the <hi>Ten Hornes</hi> do firſt <hi>make War with the Lambe,</hi> and are <hi>overcome</hi> by Him before they do this <hi>Work</hi> upon the <hi>Whore,</hi> is alſo clear from ver. 14. It may not be ſuppoſed, that while the <hi>ten Horns</hi> do remain upon the <hi>Beast</hi> that <hi>carryeth the Whore,</hi> as they appear in verſe 7. ſhould do this Work, for that would be <hi>Satan</hi> againſt himſelf; The <hi>ten Horns</hi> do hold forth the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Dominion</hi> of the <hi>ten Kingdoms</hi> or <hi>Nations</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> which had dependence upon the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and they are firſt ſeen upon the <hi>Dragon</hi> (Rev. 12.) without <hi>Crowns,</hi> which do hold forth (as hath been ſhewed) the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> in its <hi>Civil, Pagan,</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> State. Secondly, The <hi>ten Horns</hi> are ſeen in the <hi>Roman Antichriſtian</hi> State, upon the <hi>Beaſt that carryeth the Whore,</hi> and that continues <hi>fourty and two Months,</hi> and in that State they have the <hi>Crowns</hi> upon them, having <hi>received Power as Kings one hour with the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13. 1. Chap. 17.12. In this State they make war with the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and being by him and <hi>thoſe that are on his ſide,</hi> overcome and ſo broken off from the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> the <hi>ten Horns</hi> viz. the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> of thoſe Nations is <hi>given to the Saints</hi> upon the account of Chriſt, and ſo is divolved into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Stone</hi> that broke them off from the <hi>Image,</hi> and ſo are brought to their true ſtation to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>King of Nations, who hath on his Veſture, and on his Thigh a name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, KING of KINGS and LORD of LORDS;</hi> and in this State I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>ten Horns, viz.</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of thoſe Nations in the hands of the <hi>Saints</hi> is ſet againſt the <hi>Whore</hi> (or falſe Church) <hi>to execute the vengeance for the blood of the Prophets, and Saints that is found in her,</hi> thereby to accompliſh his deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this I underſtand by the <hi>ten Horns hating the Whore, and burning her fleſh with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. <hi>That the deſtroying of Babylon is not work fit for Saints to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in, being raviſhing of Women, daſhing children against the Walls, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 13.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, This is ſpoken of litterall <hi>Babylon, the Glory of the Chaldees,</hi> ver. 19. which was to be deſtroyed by the <hi>Medes,</hi> ver. 17. And if we may credit Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, they tell us, that ſuch things were fulfilled by the <hi>Medes</hi> upon <hi>Babylon</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> who had done the like upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> complains of in the Book of <hi>Lamentations,</hi> And though this <hi>Babylon</hi> did Type out ſpirituall <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet it may not be expected that every circumſtance ſhould be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and that litterally upon ſpiritual <hi>Babylon:</hi> For if it ſhould be kept to, as a Rule, that every circumſtance muſt litterally be fulfilled in the Antitype, We ſhould run upon many miſtakes about <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Work</hi> in Goſpel dayes; Alſo <hi>Raviſhing of Women,</hi> and <hi>daſhing of Children,</hi> may agree with other Scriptures to be applyed ſpiritually; upon the whole it may not be gathered, that there is any Work to be done in the rewarding of Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> which may not become Gods <hi>ſanctified Ones,</hi> eſpecially conſidering that it is the Lords <hi>controverſie,</hi> and the execution of his <hi>Righteous Judgment,</hi> and <hi>vengeance</hi> upon her.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:192321:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. That becauſe <hi>the Medes deſtroyed litterall</hi> Babylon, <hi>the like may be expected for the Nations to destroy Spiritual</hi> Babylon, <hi>and that</hi> the Earth ſhall help the Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16. <hi>And the Saints being engaged by their Faith and Prayers, the Work is ſometimes attributed to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, It is clear from Scripture, that there is a <hi>Babylon</hi> which the Saints muſt deſtroy, (as hath been already ſhewed) and it was not litteral <hi>Babylon,</hi> for the <hi>Medes</hi> deſtroyed that, Therefore it muſt be the <hi>Babylon</hi> in the New Teſtament day. Secondly, Though the <hi>Earth helps the Woman,</hi> whilſt in her ſuffering State to prevent the Devils deſtroying her; yet it is not ſaid, neither will it follow, that the <hi>Earth</hi> muſt <hi>reward Babylon.</hi> And thirdly, (as hath been already ſhewed, the Saints ſhall be uſed by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and alſo in a Hoſtile way with <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial weapons;</hi> and therefore I ſhall add no more to this Objection.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral other Objections that I meet with at this day, As that <hi>the VVork must be done by the Spirit only, and God needeth not to uſe Inſtruments; And that this is a bloody work not meet for Goſpel Saints; And that this was the</hi> Munſter <hi>Principle; And thoſe that are of this mind are carnal and neglect Soul work; and leave the wayes of God; And neglect the Converſion of ſinners, and the building up ſuch as are converted; And that they are ſuch as are againſt Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> &amp;c. But it would be too large to ſpeak to all theſe things, and to ſhew, how in the building of the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Second Temple,</hi> and many other things which God did by his Spirit, yet conferred that honour upon his <hi>Servants</hi> to uſe them as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> in his hand, though he had no need of them, but as in the <hi>Creation</hi> might do all by the word of his Power. He had no need of <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, Samuel, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and many others, he could have done his work alone, yet it was and is his pleaſure to uſe them. And as for the High Charges that are brought againſt this Truth and the Profeſſors of it, I ſhall not undertake to vindicate and plead for all that go under the name of owners of theſe things. I know there was a <hi>Judas</hi> amongſt the <hi>twelve Diſciples,</hi> yea and <hi>Peter</hi> who was very eminent did miſcarry, and the beſt of Saints here do ſtand by Faith, yet this I may ſay that the Principles teach no ſuch things, but 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. if <hi>we look for ſuch things,</hi> we are from thence inſtructed to <hi>be holy in all manner of converſation.</hi> But I hope as I have not received theſe things either with reſpect to Perſons or things, but as it might appear to be the mind of the Lord, ſo I would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or entertain hard thoughts of any of the <hi>Truths of Chriſt,</hi> becauſe many of the Profeſſors thereof walk unſuitable to their profeſſion; And to what is falſly charged upon the Perſons, or Principles, is no more then hath been upon other truths of Chriſt, and upon his followers in former ages; <hi>Caleb,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> becauſe they were faithful, and declared the truth, the whole <hi>Congregation</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing <hi>Iſrael</hi> bade <hi>ſtone them with ſtones. Num.</hi> 14. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> for declaring the truth was not onely reproached by falſe reports, but <hi>caſt into the Dungeon</hi> for his faithfulneſs, by the very <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he received more favour from the <hi>Heathens,</hi> then he did from the Profeſſors, as from <hi>Ebedmelech,</hi> the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, and from the <hi>King of Babylon Jer.</hi> 15.10. chap. 20.10. chap. 38.4.6.7-11.12. Chap. 39.11.12. and to our Lord Chriſt himſelf his friends ſaid he was <hi>beſide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> Mark 3.21. The ſtrict ſort of the <hi>Jewes</hi> did contemn him, and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192321:11"/>
and ſaid he was a <hi>Samaritane and had a Devil.</hi> Yea that Sect <hi>was every where ſpoken againſt</hi> Acts 28.22. &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> was charged to be <hi>a peſtilent fellow,</hi> and that he Preached that men ſhould <hi>do evil that good might come;</hi> Conſidering this <hi>cloud of witneſſes</hi> and how much <hi>Satan</hi> is engaged againſt the <hi>Righteous Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and how truth in all ages hath been firſt branded for error, and then op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and perſecuted, and the Profeſſors thereof Impriſoned, Baniſhed, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, I am (through Grace) helped with comfort and cheerfulneſſe to bear theſe ſore reproaches as a part of Chriſts, and Truths livery, and leave it till <hi>the day of Deciſion</hi> when the Lord will ſhew who was for Chriſt and his Truth and who were the oppoſers of them. And as to that part of the charge that <hi>we are againſt Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,</hi> the Lord in his own time will clear his deſpiſed Remnant of that with other falſe charges, and will make it manifeſt, that through rich Grace, we do own, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and witneſs for, the true Magiſtracy which is according to the Word of God, in oppoſition to the falſe Magiſtracy of Antichriſt, and of the Apoſtacy at this day; and if to be for the Houſe, and Kingdom of <hi>David,</hi> againſt wicked <hi>Saul,</hi> as was the Houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> and divers others, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.10. cha. 3.2. or for <hi>David</hi> againſt <hi>Abſalom</hi> as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. or for <hi>Solomon</hi> againſt <hi>Adonijah</hi> as was <hi>Nathan</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſee 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1. or with <hi>Ehud</hi> againſt <hi>Eglou</hi> as <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.14. or for <hi>Joaſh</hi> againſt <hi>Athaliah</hi> as was <hi>Jehoiada</hi> and others ſee 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11. or to be for the Lord and his Truth againſt <hi>Amaziah</hi> when he turned from following the Lord; in a word, if to be for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> againſt the <hi>Devil, Antichriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> be to be <hi>Vile</hi> and to be <hi>Tranſgreſſors,</hi> we are ſuch, and I deſire the Lord may keep us ſo to the end; But if theſe things be juſtifiable by Scripture and owned by the Lord, let thoſe that reproach us take heed leaſt they become fighters againſt God.</p>
            <p>The Fourth general head that I propounded to ſpeak to, is the <hi>Time</hi> of this works taking place in the world, (to wit) of the <hi>Setting up</hi> the <hi>fifth</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of the <hi>Fourth Kingdom.</hi> As for the day or year, the Lord in wiſdom hath reſerved to himſelf, and what is written of it in the Scriptures, may through our ignorance admit of many doubts and various apprehenſions; I do Judge it hath been the failing of ſome, (whom I have much honoured in the Lord) to fix the <hi>day</hi> and <hi>year,</hi> and I have deſired to be alwayes waiting for it, but not ſo fix the time, onely in general, <hi>That this Kingdom of Chriſt ſhall be ſet up in the world before his Perſonal Coming, though it ſhall not come to its perfect Glory and Beauty till he comes with his glorified Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt Argument to clear this is <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. <hi>In the dayes of theſe Kings ſhall the God of heaven ſet up a Kingdom.</hi> firſt that this <hi>Kingdom</hi> is the <hi>Fifth King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> hath been already ſhewed. Secondly, by <hi>theſe Kings</hi> I underſtand the <hi>Toes of the Image</hi> which in <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. are called <hi>Horns,</hi> and explained to be <hi>Kings;</hi> Now it muſt be granted by all, that thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> do either refer to <hi>thoſe Kings,</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.17. which are (as hath been ſhewed) the <hi>four Monarchies of the world</hi> and are held forth by the ſeveral parts of the <hi>Image, Dan.</hi> 2. or to the <hi>ten Horns</hi> (or <hi>Kings</hi>) before mentioned. Firſt it cannot be the <hi>four Monarchies,</hi> for then the <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> muſt take place in the world betwixt the time of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels</hi> going into the 70. <hi>years Captivity in Babylon,</hi> and their return to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192321:12"/>
for the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Monarchy <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Head of Gold</hi> (which was the firſt of the four Kings) had not its beginning as part of the <hi>Image,</hi> till about the time of their going into the captivity, and was taken away or deſtroyed ſeveral years before the return of the captives as may appear. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. Therefore if it were in the dayes of <hi>thoſe Kings</hi> it muſt begin while the <hi>Chaldean Monarchy</hi> was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; But it is without doubt that the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not begin in that time, but either long before, or long after; <hi>Secondly</hi> if it ſhould be true (as ſome affirm) that this <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> began either at Chriſts coming in the fleſh, or at his Reſurrection, or Aſcention, or at the <hi>pouring out</hi> of the <hi>Spirit, Acts</hi> 2. Yet it cannot be the dayes of the <hi>four Kings;</hi> For three of theſe four were come and gone many years before Chriſt, and it is evident from Scripture that the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Fourth Kingdom</hi> by which the <hi>daily ſacrifice was taken away,</hi> was in its glory in Chriſts day and had the world under <hi>his Dominion.</hi> Luke 2.1. <hi>Laſtly</hi> it cannot be the <hi>four Kings,</hi> but muſt be <hi>the Toes</hi> (or) <hi>Horns,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Cutting</hi> out of <hi>the Stone,</hi> or ſetting up the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is not ſeen till ſometime after the <hi>Image</hi> in all its parts did appear; <hi>Thou ſaweſt till that a Stone was cut out</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 34. ſo that the very <hi>Toes viz.</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtian Kings (that receive Power as Kings one hour with the Beaſt)</hi> are up ſometime before the <hi>Stone,</hi> and are them that the <hi>Stone ſmites</hi> or falls upon. verſ. 34. and the <hi>Stone</hi> muſt <hi>ſmite</hi> Imediately upon its cutting out, becauſe it breaks its way through the laſt part of the <hi>Image</hi> Government and fills up the roome of it. And therefore <hi>theſe Kings</hi> muſt be the <hi>Antichriſtian Kings</hi> which are in being when the <hi>God of Heaven ſets up</hi> the <hi>Kingdom; Secondly</hi> by <hi>the dayes of theſe Kings,</hi> I underſtand the time of their Government, or while their <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> is up in the world, and in the time that God hath permitted them to reign; now <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal coming ſhall not be in their <hi>dayes,</hi> but in his own <hi>day,</hi> when their dayes are ended, and there is ground to judge that their dayes muſt be ended ſometime before Chriſts coming in Perſon, for we read, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. that <hi>theſe Kings make War with the Lamb and are overcome,</hi> and there appears to be the end of the <hi>ten Antichriſtian Kings,</hi> which muſt be before <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonall coming, for at that coming it may not be ſuppoſed that the <hi>ten Horns</hi> ſhall make <hi>War with him,</hi> but the War is with the <hi>Lamb</hi> in his <hi>Saints,</hi> and in his <hi>Cauſe;</hi> Now if the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> muſt be ſet up, or the <hi>Stone cut out</hi> in the dayes of the <hi>ten Antichriſtian Kings,</hi> then it could not be ſet up before, nor at the Aſcention of Chriſt; For thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> in that <hi>State,</hi> were not then in being, the laſt <hi>Beaſt</hi> that comes from Hell was not up, therefore it muſt be before Chriſts Perſonal coming from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> becauſe their dayes are ended before or at that coming.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second ground</hi> to clear this truth is from <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.1. <hi>The Lord</hi> (that is God the Father) <hi>ſaid unto my Lord</hi> (that is Chriſt) <hi>ſet thou at my right hand till I make thine enemies thy footſtool.</hi> By Chriſts <hi>enemies,</hi> I unde ſtand, not onely the <hi>Antichriſtian State,</hi> but it includes the whole world, who through the Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil are againſt Chriſt and would not have him <hi>to Reign Pſal.</hi> 2.1.2.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17.18. Secondly by the <hi>enemies,</hi> being made <hi>his footſtool</hi> I underſtand not a Total deſtruction of their perſons, but a taking away and deſtroying of their <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and bringing them to the <hi>foot</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be as the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192321:12"/>
               <hi>Stool</hi> for his <hi>Government</hi> to take place upon, or to bring them under and in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to it. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſitting at the <hi>Right hand of the Father,</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his Perſonal being in Heaven as our Advocate where he is ſaid to be at <hi>the right hand of the Majeſty on high,</hi> Col. 3.1. Heb. 1.3. cha. 8.1. that ſo if <hi>Chriſts</hi> enemies muſt be brought down, and his <hi>Government</hi> take place whileſt he ſits <hi>at the Right hand of God,</hi> Then the Kingdom <hi>of Chriſt</hi> muſt be ſet up before his Perſonal coming.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third ground</hi> is taken from the time of <hi>Babylons</hi> deſtruction, which muſt be before <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal coming; And <hi>Babylon</hi> being to be deſtroyed by the <hi>Saints, Stone,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> this work muſt take place before the Perſonal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; That <hi>Babylons</hi> fall by the <hi>Plagues</hi> muſt be before <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal coming, conſider <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>come out of her my people that ye pertake not of her ſins and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> God here ſpeaks to thoſe that were not ſo much his people by viſible profe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion for they were in <hi>Babylon,</hi> but ſuch as by ſpecial Grace (as the fruit of Electing love) he calls his people, and theſe are ſuch as <hi>ſhall be caught up,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.17. to meet <hi>Chriſt at his</hi> Perſonal <hi>coming,</hi> and Phil. 3.21. 1 Joh. 3.2. <hi>Have their vile bodies changed, and faſhioned like unto his Glorious body</hi> and ſo muſt be out of the reach of ſuch temporal plagues as muſt come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Babylon,</hi> but <hi>Babylons plagues</hi> muſt come in a time when Gods own peculiar people may through <hi>ſin</hi> come to pertake of them, and therefore the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt needs be before <hi>Chriſts</hi> perſonal coming; that word, <hi>Dan</hi> 7.26. ſpeaking of the <hi>little Horn,</hi> ſaith <hi>they ſhall take away his Dominion to conſume and deſtroy it unto the end,</hi> which <hi>end,</hi> muſt be the end of the fourth <hi>Monarchy</hi> or of this old world, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come in perſon and <hi>the world to come,</hi> (ſpoken of <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.) take place, ſo that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> muſt be a deſtroying and conſuming as a gradual work till the end of the fourth <hi>Monarchy; The Stone,</hi> Dan. 2. that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Antichriſtian State</hi> muſt do it before <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes in perſon; it doth it not at once as it would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f it were to be done at <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal coming who comes <hi>as the lightning:</hi> but is done gradually as may appear by the ſcope of the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fourth Ground</hi> is taken from the <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments</hi> that ſhall be uſed in the <hi>work,</hi> and they (as it hath been proved) muſt be the <hi>Saints</hi> with <hi>Material, weapons</hi> in a Military way, and I ſuppoſe I need not take up time to ſhew that it is inconſiſtent with a glorified <hi>Saint</hi> to do this work with Material weapons in the way that it is to be done, for I never met with any of that perſwaſion, to wit, <hi>that Glorified Saints might ſo uſe Material weapons,</hi> and that the <hi>Saints</hi> ſhall be <hi>all changed</hi> and have glorified bodies is clear from, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. So then if the <hi>Saints</hi> muſt be the <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> and the <hi>work</hi> not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with their glorified State, the <hi>work muſt needs</hi> take place before the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal coming of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fifth Ground</hi> is taken from the <hi>Sitting</hi> of the <hi>Judgment</hi> menc. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26. by <hi>the Ju gment</hi> cannot be underſtood the laſt <hi>judgment</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. but muſt be the <hi>Judgement of Antichriſt</hi> menc. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1. which is the judging, and paſſing the ſentence againſt <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp; for the <hi>righteous cauſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and this doth Imediately precede the <hi>vengeance</hi> mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6, 10. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7, 26. <hi>they ſhall take
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192321:13"/>
away his Dominion.</hi> Now this <hi>Judgment</hi> ſits before Chriſts Perſonal coming, yea and the <hi>vengeance executed</hi> according to this <hi>Judgment</hi> is before that coming; For firſt, he ſaith, <hi>the Judgment ſhall ſit,</hi> and then <hi>they ſhall take away his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to conſume it unto the end.</hi> Now <hi>the ſitting of the Judgment</hi> and the <hi>executing</hi> of the <hi>vengance,</hi> being the ſame with the <hi>God of Heaven's ſetting up the Kingdom,</hi> and all this being before Chriſts Perſonall comming, doth further clear this Truth.</p>
            <p>The Sixth Ground is taken from the <hi>pouring out of the Vialls,</hi> Rev. 16. The <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls</hi> do containe and are called <hi>the ſeven laſt Plagues,</hi> that muſt accompliſh the deſtruction of the Anti hriſtian world, and do much agree with the <hi>VVork</hi> of the <hi>Stone</hi> in <hi>Daniel</hi> 2. Now theſe <hi>Vialls</hi> or ſix of them, muſt be <hi>poured out</hi> before Chriſts perſonal comming. <hi>First,</hi> becauſe they do the <hi>VVork</hi> gradually, and therefore are ſeven <hi>Vialls,</hi> otherwiſe one <hi>Viall</hi> (if it were at Chriſts coming) would do all the Work. Secondly, They do the deſtroying Work, which (as hath been proved) muſt be done before Chriſts Perſonal coming, and if the <hi>Vialls</hi> do the ſame Work with the <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and ſix, if not all, muſt be poured forth before Chriſts Perſonal coming, then the Work muſt take place before that coming. As againſt all Truths there are ſeveral Objections, ſo againſt this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is objected, and alleadged <hi>That the Saints must be in a Suffering ſtate till Christ comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a Twofold Suffering; the one by the Antichriſtian bondage, and ſlavery, the other by corruption and inward temptations; From the firſt, the Saints ſhall be delivered before Chriſts coming, (as hath been ſhewed) the other may remain till Chriſt at his coming <hi>binds Satan,</hi> and <hi>changeth our vile bodies.</hi> Alſo there is a twofold coming of Chriſt in the <hi>latter day,</hi> the one a comming by his Spirit in his Saints-to the Work of <hi>executing vengeance,</hi> and ſo Chriſt is the <hi>Stone;</hi> and ſo he overcomes the <hi>ten Hornes;</hi> and ſo he comes <hi>at midnight</hi> when the <hi>Virgins ſleep;</hi> and ſo he <hi>comes as a Thief;</hi> and this is the Coming ſpoken of <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>And ſhall not God avenge his own Elect? Nevertheleſſe when the Son of man cometh, ſhall he find Faith on the Earth?</hi> Till this coming the Saints were to be in a ſuffering State upon both the former &amp; the latter Accounts. The ſecond is, his Perſonal coming with all <hi>his Saints,</hi> and <hi>all the holy Angels,</hi> when <hi>every eye ſhall ſee him;</hi> This ſhall not only be a coming in <hi>Power,</hi> but alſo with <hi>great Glory;</hi> before this coming the Saints ſhall be in the Poſeſſion of the Government upon the account of <hi>Christ</hi> who is the rightful <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls</hi> or Six of them ſhall be poured forth, by which much of the <hi>vengeance</hi> that is to be <hi>executed</hi> ſhall be accompliſhed upon the Earth; But although the Saints ſhall be in the Government of the Nations, under and on the behalf of <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> yet the <hi>Devil</hi> being not <hi>bound,</hi> ſhall go forth full of <hi>Rage,</hi> becauſe the time of his binding is near, and immediatly before the Perſonal coming of <hi>Christ</hi> ſhall ſtir up the <hi>Nations</hi> to rebell againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Saints,</hi> and the Nations ſhall raiſe War againſt the Saints, and ſhall take the <hi>City of Jeruſalem,</hi> and it ſhall be a <hi>time</hi> of great <hi>trouble,</hi> and <hi>then ſhall the Lord go forth, and fight againſt thoſe Nations as when he fought in the day of Battel,</hi> and then the <hi>Seventh Viall</hi> ſhall be <hi>poured forth into the air,</hi> which holds forth the making a full and perfect end of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192321:13"/>
the <hi>VVork:</hi> my apprehenſions in this matter are grounded upon <hi>Eze.</hi> 39. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.1.2, 3, 4. <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.16. chap. 19.17.18.19. and ſeveral other Scriptures which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late unto, and muſt have their fulfilling in this time; In the underſtanding of the weighty matters which relate to the <hi>latter day,</hi> I would commend two things to conſideration, which may through the bleſſing of God be very helpful and uſeful to prevent miſtakes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To wait upon God for his Spirit in the ſearch of the Scriptures, for a right diſtinction of the ſeveral <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Seaſons:</hi> as Firſt, the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſuffering State: the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Antichriſts Reign:</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Chriſts coming</hi> by his Spirit, in the <hi>Saints to execute</hi> the <hi>vengeance:</hi> the <hi>Time of his Perſonal coming:</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> of the <hi>thouſand years Reign:</hi> The end of the <hi>thouſand years:</hi> and the <hi>laſt Judgement,</hi> when he <hi>ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to the Father;</hi> And as theſe times ſhould be diſtinctly conſidered, without miſplacing them, or cauſing the one to claſh againſt the other: ſo, The <hi>Second</hi> thing to be conſidered, is through the ſpirit diligently to ſearch the <hi>Promiſes, Propheſies,</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> of this <hi>Latter day work</hi> contained in the holy Scriptures, and before we paſſe judgement upon any of them, to wait upon the Lord for a right underſtanding of the reſpective <hi>Times</hi> unto which the <hi>Promiſe, Propheſie</hi> or <hi>Type</hi> doth relate: for if we go to open then and not Firſt underſtand what <hi>Time</hi> they relate unto, we are in danger of very great miſtakes: and this, I judge, is much of the cauſe of the great differences that are among even thoſe of the <hi>People of God,</hi> that <hi>Wait</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom</hi> at this day, and through this miſtake the poor <hi>Jews</hi> ſtumbled and fell, miſplacing thoſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Propheſies,</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> that did relate to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that day; if theſe <hi>two things</hi> be diligently obſerved, it would ſave much labour in anſwering ſeveral <hi>Objections:</hi> ſome of which not yet ſpoken to are as followeth.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>That Chriſt muſt be firſt in the poſſeſſion of this Glory, he being the Captain that was firſt made perfect through ſuffering, and therefore the Kingdom muſt not be ſet up till his Perſonal coming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This ariſeth moſtly from a miſtake: for though <hi>the Saints ſhall take and poſſeſſe the Kingdom</hi> before <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal appearing: yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall be firſt in the <hi>Glory</hi> of it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. It is <hi>given to Chriſt:</hi> and the opening of it in verſe the 18. ſaith, that <hi>the Saints ſhall take the Kingdom:</hi> though all this while <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his perſon is in heaven; for firſt, <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt <hi>have the preheminence,</hi> to be firſt in the <hi>Glory,</hi> as the <hi>Saints</hi> by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> do obtain it. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They do not onely obtain it by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but alſo upon the Ground of his <hi>Authority</hi> as he is <hi>King of Kings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They do it by his <hi>Command</hi> (all which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the foregoing diſcourſe, upon the <hi>Saints</hi> being the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> in the <hi>work</hi>) and ſo the <hi>Glory</hi> of the Conqueſt is to the <hi>Lamb</hi> Rev. 17.14. The <hi>Lamb ſhall overcome them,</hi> &amp;c. Revel. 4.10. The <hi>Crowns</hi> are <hi>caſt before him,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> do <hi>take</hi> and <hi>exerciſe</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> for, and on the behalf of <hi>Chriſt</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.18.) <hi>his Crown ſhall flouriſh; It is further objected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. 2 Tim. 4.1. <hi>His appearing is joyned with, yea put before his Kingdom; even when he ſhall judge both the quick and the dead, therefore his Kingdom ſhall not take place before his appearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though <hi>his Appearing</hi> be here joyned with, and placed before his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> yet the Scripture doth not ſay, neither by the order of words can it be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192321:14"/>
ſafely gathered, that his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall not begin till his <hi>appearing:</hi> and thoſe that conſider the <hi>Spirits Method</hi> in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> may know, that ofttimes, thoſe things that are to be performed <hi>Laſt,</hi> are placed <hi>Firſt;</hi> and ſometimes words do reſpect a thing in its beginning, and ſometimes in its perfection, as 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Make your calling, and Election,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe that own <hi>Election</hi> according to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: will grant that it takes place before <hi>Calling:</hi> and yet <hi>Calling</hi> is here placed before it. So <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> applies the <hi>blotting out of ſin,</hi> to the time of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Perſonal <hi>coming:</hi> when according to other Scriptures the <hi>blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out,</hi> or <hi>forgiveneſs of ſin,</hi> takes place long before, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. ſo that this word muſt reſpect the perfecting of it. In <hi>Luke</hi> 21.28. you have the like word applied to <hi>Redemptions</hi> taking place, at <hi>the coming of Chriſt:</hi> the like in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. though by other Scriptures, <hi>Redemption</hi> hath its beginning long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. and if theſe things be conſidered: it may appear that either the <hi>Kingdom</hi> in this place of 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. muſt reſpect the perfection of its <hi>Glory,</hi> which ſhall not be till <hi>Chriſts Perſonal coming:</hi> though as hath been ſhewed it muſt have its beginning before: or if it ſhould reſpect its firſt taking place, we may not build ſo much upon the order of the words as to make them claſh againſt, yea to exclude the ſcope of many Scriptures which do clearly hold forth the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> taking place before the Perſonal <hi>appearing</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second thing</hi> that I ſhall lay down with reſpect to the <hi>Time</hi> of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> taking place, is. <hi>That it muſt begin, or take place amongſt the Gentile Saints before the Call of the Nation of the Jewes</hi> (to wit) <hi>the Natural Seed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Ground of this:</hi> I gather from the <hi>Work, Time,</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Vials,</hi> Rev. 16. <hi>Six</hi> of them are to be <hi>poured forth</hi> before the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> (which I underſtand to be the <hi>Natural Seed of Abraham</hi>) have <hi>their way prepared.</hi> The <hi>Sixth Vial</hi> Rev. 16.12. muſt be <hi>poured out upon the great River Euphrates,</hi> that <hi>the way of the Kings of the Eaſt might be prepared;</hi> By <hi>the River Euphrates,</hi> I underſtand, not the Material <hi>River,</hi> for the <hi>ſhips of Tarſhiſh</hi> muſt bring them over greater Rivers then that: and that <hi>River</hi> cannot block up their <hi>way,</hi> but it is the <hi>Power</hi> of that people (to wit the <hi>Turks</hi>) that have their Scituation about that <hi>River.</hi> By <hi>Rivers,</hi> and <hi>waters</hi> is elſewhere to be underſtood of <hi>Earthly Powers,</hi> as in <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.4. compare with verſ. 6. and <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.15. and alſo at this day the <hi>Turks</hi> do poſſeſſe the <hi>Land of Judea,</hi> and it muſt be the breaking of their <hi>Power</hi> that <hi>prepares the way for the Kings of the Eaſt;</hi> Now <hi>the Vials,</hi> doing the ſame <hi>work</hi> with the <hi>Stone,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> (to wit the <hi>deſtroying of Antichriſt</hi>) and they doing the <hi>work</hi> or moſt of it, before the <hi>Call</hi> of the <hi>Jews:</hi> the <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt needs take place alſo before their <hi>Call;</hi> I have not heard of any that denyes that the <hi>Kings of the Eaſt,</hi> are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Abrahams Natural Seed,</hi> and therefore ſhall ſpeak no further to this <hi>Ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Ground,</hi> from whence I gather that the <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt <hi>take place</hi> before the <hi>Jews Call,</hi> is this; The <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Kingdom ſmites the Image upon the Feet,</hi> (to wit the <hi>Babyloniſh State</hi>) and this <hi>ſmiting</hi> muſt be done by thoſe of the People of God that were under <hi>Babylons yoke,</hi> Rev. 18.4.6. Zech. 2.7. They
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192321:14"/>
that are under <hi>Babylons yoke</hi> in this <hi>New Teſtament</hi> day, are not the <hi>Jews,</hi> but the <hi>Gentile Saints,</hi> therefore the <hi>work</hi> muſt firſt take place amongſt them: The <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſtrikes the firſt ſtroke upon the <hi>Antichriſtian State,</hi> Dan. 2.44.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Ground</hi> of this Aſſertion is, That the <hi>Kingdom</hi> or <hi>Stone</hi> muſt <hi>break</hi> and make way for the <hi>Jewes</hi> before their coming in, therefore it muſt take place or be in being, before it breaks the way; The <hi>Gentile</hi> Saints, muſt be uſed as the <hi>Instruments</hi> in breaking the way for, and bringing in the <hi>Jewes,</hi> Iſa. 49.22. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 66.20.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>That many of the Scriptures which referr to the Work of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, do ſpeak to the People of God, who are to be uſed in it, under thoſe Names, and Titles, that properly relate to the natural Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>as</hi> Jacob, Zion, Jeruſalem, Judah, <hi>and</hi> Iſrael. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That although in the <hi>Old Covenant</hi> day (in which the being one of <hi>Abrahams</hi> natural <hi>Seed</hi> did intitle to <hi>Church-Memberſhip</hi>) the viſible <hi>Church</hi> was diſtinguiſhed by thoſe <hi>Names,</hi> and <hi>Titles:</hi> yet it may not be alwaies reſtrained or applyed to them in <hi>Goſpel</hi> dayes, when their <hi>Typical Church State</hi> comes to ceaſe; and as their <hi>Church State</hi> was <hi>Typical:</hi> ſo was the <hi>Titles</hi> that God gave to them: and the names of <hi>Jacob, Zion,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> do truly and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally relate to the <hi>Goſpel</hi> or <hi>New Covenant Church,</hi> in which, neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile,</hi> have any right by natural Generation, but by <hi>Faith in Chriſt,</hi> who <hi>is all and in all,</hi> Col. 3.11. and ſo in him (2 Cor. 1.20.) we come to have a right to <hi>all the Promiſes</hi> that are held forth to <hi>Jacob,</hi> or <hi>Zion,</hi> &amp;c. So Pſal. 102.13.16. in which Scripture <hi>Zion</hi> muſt reſpect the <hi>Goſpel Church,</hi> which the Lord ſhall build <hi>when he appears in his glory.</hi> It is the <hi>Goſpel Church</hi> that (<hi>Zech.</hi> 2.7.) <hi>dwells with the Daughter of Babylon,</hi> Gal. 4.26. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14. which with many other Scriptures doth clearly demonſtrate, theſe Titles are moſt truly to be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Goſpel Church,</hi> and thoſe that deny this, muſt exclude the <hi>Goſpel Church</hi> from the benefit of the greateſt part of the <hi>Promiſes</hi> in Scripture; and though this may ſeem to cut off the <hi>Jewes</hi> from their Priviledges: yet it will rather and more truly inveſt them therein upon a more Noble account, when they ſhall come to embrace the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> and thus much to this Objection.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to ſpeak of <hi>Two Scriptures,</hi> that are ſpecially inſiſted upon, by thoſe who expect the <hi>Work</hi> to begin among the <hi>Jewes:</hi> the one in <hi>Micha</hi> 4.8. <hi>Unto thee O Tower of the Flock, ſhall come the firſt Dominion, &amp;c.</hi> If this ſhould be referred to the Naturall <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Abraham:</hi> it can only reſpect the <hi>two Tribes,</hi> to wit, <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin:</hi> and all that may be gathered in this matter from it, is, that the <hi>Kingdom ſhall come to the two Tribes,</hi> before the <hi>Ten,</hi> which will much agree with other Scriptures; but it will not follow from the Scope of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in the words, that the <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall not take place, and be in being among the <hi>Gentile</hi> Saints before its <hi>Dominion</hi> comes to the <hi>two Tribes,</hi> becauſe they muſt have the <hi>firſt Dominion,</hi> before the other <hi>ten Tribes.</hi> The other Scripture is <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.7. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſave the Tents of</hi> Judah, <hi>first, that the glory of the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and the glory of the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>do not magnifie themſelves againſt</hi> Judah. By <hi>Judah</hi> or the <hi>Tents</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> I underſtand the <hi>two Tribes:</hi> and by the <hi>glory of the Houſe of David,</hi> and <hi>the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:192321:15"/>
the <hi>Ten Tribes;</hi> For the <hi>Glory was,</hi> to have the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> in conjunction with the <hi>Two,</hi> abiding with the <hi>Houſe of David;</hi> but when the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> revolted, the Kingdom was rent, and <hi>the Glory of the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem</hi> went off; and that the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> might not <hi>magnify themſelves</hi> againſt the <hi>Two Tribes,</hi> who (<hi>Hoſea.</hi> 11.12.) <hi>Ruled with God and was faithful with the Saints</hi> long after the revolt of the <hi>Ten:</hi> the Lord will (in the <hi>Latter day) ſave</hi> the <hi>two Tribes first,</hi> which is all that can be gathered in this matter from this Scripture, and it will not prove that the <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall firſt take place or begin amongſt the naturall <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but I ſhall add no more to this, but come to ſpeak to the third <hi>particular</hi> relating to the <hi>Time</hi> of this <hi>Work taking place,</hi> and to that I ſhall lay down this Poſition.</p>
            <p>Poſition, <hi>That the Work of deſtroying the Fourth, and ſetting up the Fifth Kingdom is begun, and hath taken place amongst us in this Iſle of great Brittain.</hi> And in entering upon the proof of this, I ſhall for the making way, preſent ſome particular Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>As firſt, That the <hi>Beaſt with the Seven Heads</hi> and <hi>Ten Hornes,</hi> mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. and alſo the <hi>Whore</hi> mentioned in the ſame Chapter, have their <hi>Riſe, Seat, Dominion,</hi> and <hi>Reign,</hi> in this part of the World called <hi>Europe,</hi> where the <hi>Roman,</hi> or <hi>Fourth Kingdom</hi> had its place, before, at, and ſince the <hi>coming of Chriſt</hi> in the fleſh: and though the <hi>Riſe,</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Power</hi> is changed from the <hi>meerly Civil,</hi> to the groſſe <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> or <hi>Mixed</hi> State, yet thoſe that will ſearch the Hiſtories, may find, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath taken and doth keep the ſame Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that were belonging to the <hi>Civil State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Conſideration</hi> is, That this <hi>Nation</hi> or the <hi>Power</hi> of this <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> hath been accounted, and really is, one of the <hi>Ten Hornes</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or <hi>Toes</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> and was joyned with the <hi>Antichristian Beaſt</hi> very ſoon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving <hi>Power as a King one hour with him,</hi> according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. and the <hi>Whore</hi> or <hi>falſe Church,</hi> hath been long mounted upon the <hi>Civil,</hi> or <hi>Beastly</hi> Power in this Nation. It is now above one thouſand years, as hiſtory relates, ſince <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> the <hi>Monck</hi> was ſent over by the <hi>Pope</hi> into this Nation, where he found great incouragement from the <hi>Civil Powers,</hi> which <hi>Satan</hi> had fitted for his own deſign of carrying the <hi>Whore; Proud Auguſtine</hi> (for ſo he is called) doth forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſettle the <hi>National Church,</hi> and mounts it upon the <hi>Civil Power,</hi> to bear up &amp; maintain it, and many <hi>abominable wicked Lawes,</hi> were made to Anſwer the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils deſign in the upholding, and maintaining this <hi>Whoriſh Nationall Church:</hi> at the ſetting up whereof, there are found ſome <hi>Faithful Chriſtians</hi> in the Nation, which ſo far as we may credit Hiſtory, were ſome remainders of the fruits of the Miniſtry of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimatheah,</hi> who is ſaid, was the firſt Preacher of the <hi>joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſound</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in this <hi>Iſland:</hi> and theſe Chriſtians not falling down to, but witneſſing againſt the <hi>Antichriſtian Abominations,</hi> which were brought in from <hi>Rome,</hi> and readily received in this Nation: <hi>Auguſtine</hi> becomes their great enemy, and (being of that <hi>Popiſh</hi> ſtamp, that <hi>Thirſts after,</hi> and muſt be <hi>drunk with the blood of the Saints</hi>) thirſts after the blood of thoſe poor Chriſtians, who for their ſafety fled to the <hi>Mountains</hi> in <hi>Wales:</hi> but <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tho ough the help of the <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Beaſtly Power</hi> (as the beginning of the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> which <hi>God</hi> will <hi>reward</hi>)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192321:15"/>
obtains his end, and <hi>drinks the Blood,</hi> or takes away the lives of thoſe <hi>Faithfull Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> and ſo in ſhedding the <hi>blood of the Saints,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Whore</hi> were united together in this Nation, and therefore no wonder if they cleave ſo cloſe together (as at this day) till the <hi>vengeance</hi> be accompliſhed upon them. This <hi>proud Augustine</hi> being <hi>Ordained</hi> and <hi>ſent</hi> by the <hi>Pope,</hi> (whoſe <hi>power</hi> is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Hell) Ordains</hi> and Settles, <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> who <hi>Ordaine</hi> the <hi>National Miniſtry,</hi> and ſettle them in their reſpective <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> and this by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, hath continued to this day, and is the <hi>Ordination</hi> ſo much pleaded for in this Nation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Conſideration</hi> is, That the <hi>Toe, or Horne,</hi> or that part of the <hi>Beaſtly Power</hi> in <hi>Brittain</hi> which carrieth the <hi>Whore,</hi> according to the National Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was made up with, and did conſiſt of, <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth Conſideration</hi> is, That it is the proper <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> mentioned <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. to <hi>Smite</hi> and <hi>Break</hi> theſe <hi>Toes,</hi> or <hi>Hornes,</hi> and ſo by its <hi>Government</hi> to fill up the room thereof. Having layd down theſe things, I ſhall proceed to the proof of the <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> to wit, <hi>That the Work is begun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>VVork</hi> that is only proper for the <hi>Stone</hi> to do (to wit, the <hi>brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> of the <hi>Toes,</hi> or <hi>Hornes) hath taken place in this Nation;</hi> The <hi>Horn</hi> or <hi>Toe</hi> of this Nation (to wit) <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> is broken, though not yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. <hi>made as the Chaffe of the Summer threſhing Flower.</hi> Not only the <hi>King,</hi> but <hi>Kingſhip</hi> and <hi>Peeridge</hi> is broken: and not only the <hi>Commons,</hi> but the very <hi>Foundation</hi> of their <hi>Conſtitution</hi> from the <hi>Nation</hi> is broken, and God hath for ſeveral years been witneſſing againſt it. I need not ſpeak further to the proof of this, if we forget not the <hi>things which our Eyes have ſeen, Deut.</hi> 49. It is Matter of Mourning that this <hi>Generation</hi> (like <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, either underſtood not or elſe have forgotten <hi>the workes of God,</hi> and it is no wonder if God deſtroy them, <hi>and not build them up,</hi> Pſal. 28.5. Pſal. 106.7.13. Though the <hi>Stone</hi> muſt break the <hi>Horne,</hi> or <hi>Toe:</hi> it is not ſaid that it ſhould be done at one blow, or two: and therefore if God ſhould ſuffer <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> to rally again in this <hi>Nation,</hi> it may not be ſaid that the <hi>Work</hi> hath not been among us; for ſeeing the <hi>Stone</hi> may not do it at one, or two blows, the Lord may <hi>gather</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare</hi> them for the <hi>Second,</hi> or rather the <hi>Third</hi> ſtroke, till he make them as <hi>the Chaffe</hi> and they <hi>be carryed away with the wind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Work</hi> in this Nation did not end in <hi>ſmiting</hi> the <hi>Horn,</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Goverment</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did take place in its roome. When the remainder of the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> was by the anſwer of the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Lords People with an eminent hand of God broken: the undoubted right to the <hi>Throne</hi> being <hi>Chriſts</hi> (who had obtained it by his <hi>Sword,</hi> and <hi>Bow,</hi> as the fulfilling of many <hi>promiſes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Propheſies</hi> of Scripture,) the <hi>Saints</hi> (whoſe <hi>Right</hi> under <hi>Chriſt</hi> it is) upon the <hi>Account,</hi> and on the behalf of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> did not onely <hi>take,</hi> but come into the <hi>poſſeſsion</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> for by a ſpeciall hand of God, many of the <hi>Saints</hi> upon the breach of the <hi>Parliament</hi> (before mentioned) were ſent for from ſeveral parts of this <hi>Iſland,</hi> (who found the Lord ſtirring up their hearts) to come to <hi>Receive,</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſe</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> for <hi>Chriſt their King,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, when they were come together at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> was <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192321:16"/>
to them,</hi> and they (or at leaſt many of them) <hi>received</hi> it upon the <hi>avowed account of the Son of God,</hi> as the anſwer of the <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> of many of the Lords enlightned ones, as alſo by the joynt conſent of both <hi>Armies,</hi> and <hi>Navy</hi> which God had wonderfully uſed in his <hi>Work,</hi> and this word <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. was then cited in the <hi>delivering</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> to them, <hi>the Kingdom ſhall not be left to other People:</hi> but for a full underſtanding of theſe paſſages and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, I refer you to <hi>Cromwels</hi> ſpeech made to the perſons above mentioned at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> which <hi>ſpeech</hi> is Printed in A <hi>Book</hi> called the <hi>Fifth Kingdom aſſerted in oppoſition to the Beaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this people being come together upon <hi>Chriſts account,</hi> the firſt thing they do, they keep a day of ſolemn Prayer to the Lord for his preſence with them in his <hi>Work,</hi> in which day the Lord was much ſeen amongſt them as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious welcome at their coming together: But although they were all <hi>Called</hi> as <hi>men fearing God,</hi> yet there is found ſeveral perſons amongſt them, that either through ignorance, or wicked craft, prove great obſtructers of the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and prevail, for the <hi>calling</hi> that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> by the name of <hi>a Parliament,</hi> with ſome other Paſſages, that were not agreeable to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> which at this day proves a <hi>ſtumbling Block</hi> to ſome: but by the good hand of God, <hi>Kingdom Light</hi> did increaſe among that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> yea the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> grew, and appeared openly, and the falſe Spirit fell before it; the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Miniſtry</hi> were diſcountenanced and not called in to <hi>Pray</hi> among them as they expected; The <hi>Lawyers trade</hi> alſo began to fall, for in ſtead of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Heatheniſh books,</hi> the <hi>Bible</hi> was looked into, &amp; the <hi>Law of God</hi> ſearched after; <hi>A new Body</hi> or <hi>Model of the Law</hi> was Voted, by which the <hi>Old</hi> muſt needs fall; The <hi>Court of Chancery</hi> was Voted down; A <hi>Vote</hi> alſo paſſed, tending to the throwing down of <hi>Tithes,</hi> by which the <hi>Antichriſtian Miniſtry</hi> was like to fall; The <hi>Power of Patrons for preſentations</hi> to the <hi>livings</hi> of the <hi>Antichriſtian Church</hi> was taken away; The oppreſſing <hi>craft</hi> and <hi>gain</hi> of the <hi>Lawyers</hi> and <hi>National Miniſtry</hi> being ſo like to fall: they beſtir them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and endeavour to engage the <hi>Corrupt Party</hi> in that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> (and <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> with his <hi>Officers</hi>) to ſtand by them for the keeping up their Trade: the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> being got into <hi>Cromwell</hi> and many of his <hi>great Officers</hi> (who had forgotten or little minded their <hi>Ingagements</hi> to the Lord at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> and <hi>Worceſter</hi> in the day of their <hi>ſtreights:</hi> when they reſolved to proſecute the very <hi>things,</hi> which that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> were a doing, if the Lord would own, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them in thoſe difficult hours) they very readily joyn with the <hi>Zanballats,</hi> and <hi>Tobiahs</hi> of the day, to <hi>cauſe the Work of the Lord to ceaſe,</hi> and as much as in them lay to turn it back. The Lord for gracious ends, and that the <hi>Work</hi> might anſwer the <hi>Types,</hi> and <hi>Propheſies</hi> that went before of it, permits the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> to take place, and <hi>Cromwell (Judas</hi> like) entertains <hi>meetings</hi> with the <hi>Prieſts, Lawyers</hi> and <hi>Corrupt Party</hi> of that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and communes with them how he might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray this <hi>Righteous Cauſe,</hi> and the proffers of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> like the <hi>thirty pieces of ſilver</hi> to <hi>Judas,</hi> (as his actions have clearly manifeſted) did put him upon this abominable Treachery, and forthwith that <hi>wicked Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> was prepared, and falſe ſcandalous reports, and reproaches raiſed againſt, and caſt upon the <hi>faithful Members</hi> of that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> thereby to render
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192321:16"/>
them odious to the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> yea to their <hi>Brethren,</hi> (which was the very way that the <hi>Martyrs</hi> were formerly brought to ſuffering, yea <hi>Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> by the wickedneſs of that <hi>Generation</hi> did thus ſuffer) as perſons that would <hi>deſtroy Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Laws, and Propriety;</hi> It is true they were for deſtroying the <hi>Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Propriety</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> but did own, and witneſs to, the <hi>Magiſtracy Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with <hi>Propriety</hi> according to thoſe <hi>Laws:</hi> which muſt be the <hi>Salvation</hi> of this poor <hi>Iſland,</hi> if there be any left for it; upon theſe reproaches many were ready to cry out as they did of <hi>Paul Acts</hi> 22.22. <hi>away with ſuch fellowes from the Earth for it is not fit that they ſhould live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> having made its <hi>Party,</hi> and engaged the <hi>Corrupt Party of that Aſſembly,</hi> the day was appointed for breaking them up, and thereby the <hi>crucifying</hi> of the dear <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>day</hi> being come <hi>Cromwell</hi> repaires to the place appointed, (to wit <hi>Whitehall</hi>) and that <hi>Corrupt Party</hi> of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> to the <hi>Place</hi> of their ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> betimes in the morning before the uſual time of meeting: where being come: One of them begins with prayer or ſomewhat like it, fixing his eye upon the door till the <hi>Speaker</hi> came, and by that time he came in, (though the deſign was privately carryed, yet) there was ſo many of the <hi>friends of Chriſts precious Cauſe</hi> come in, as that they durſt not venture their <hi>Treacherous,</hi> and <hi>wicked deſign</hi> upon a <hi>Vote,</hi> but diſorderly and in confuſion, took up the <hi>Mace,</hi> and went away to <hi>Whitehall</hi> where pretended<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they delivered up the <hi>Government</hi> to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> I ſay pretendedly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe in reality the <hi>Government</hi> was not theirs to deliver up, <hi>but Chriſts,</hi> upon whoſe accompt it was <hi>obtained,</hi> and <hi>received,</hi> and ſo they could not really deliver it up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> who had received it, could have delivered it up, this act was neither done by <hi>Vote</hi> in, nor agreement of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> but by a company of <hi>Rebellious diſorderly perſons</hi> diſpoſſeſſing and putting themſelves out of that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> (who had received, and did poſſeſſe the <hi>Government</hi> for Chriſt) and having ſo put themſelves out, had no more <hi>Power,</hi> or <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Goverment</hi> to deliver to <hi>Cromwell:</hi> then <hi>Cromwell</hi> or any other perſons at that time had, to deliver to them: yea a <hi>company</hi> of <hi>fellowes</hi> that had met in the ſtreet, might have gone to <hi>Cromwell</hi> and delivered as much <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to him, as they did: but the undoubted <hi>Authority</hi> being with <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King of Nations,</hi> under him it did reſt with thoſe that remained in the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly,</hi> keeping the <hi>Place</hi> and following the <hi>Work</hi> which the Lord had called <hi>them to,</hi> and ſet them in, who had clearly made <hi>an eminent deciſion betwixt cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell,</hi> and <hi>cattel,</hi> the <hi>corrupt Party</hi> of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> going forth, and the <hi>Faithful Friends</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Cauſe</hi> remaining together; and though <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Officers</hi> had owned the <hi>Government</hi> to reſt in that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Avowed Account of the Son of God;</hi> yet ſo bold and Wicked, were they now become, as they ſent Col. <hi>Goffe</hi> and Lieut. Col. <hi>White,</hi> with <hi>Souldiers,</hi> (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly ſetting themſelves againſt the very <hi>Son of God,</hi> to withſtand his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and interrupt the exerciſe of his <hi>Government</hi> in the hands of his <hi>People</hi> whom he had <hi>Called,</hi> and by rich Grace ſeperated from the <hi>treacherous dealers,</hi> and kept
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192321:17"/>
together in the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> after the <hi>Corrupt Party,</hi> (before mentioned) was gone forth) which bold <hi>Apoſtates</hi> came into the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and by force of Arms turned them out: and <hi>Cromwel</hi> being ſet up by the <hi>Prieſts, Lawyers,</hi> and his <hi>trecherous Army, Aſſumes</hi> (and <hi>exalts</hi> himſelf in) the <hi>Throne,</hi> which before he had declared did belong to Chriſt; And thus the Lord did permit a <hi>Stop</hi> to be put unto, and a <hi>Death</hi> to come upon the <hi>Glorious Work</hi> &amp; <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to break forth, and take place in the midſt of us, and ſo a turning <hi>back to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, building again the things</hi> which the Lord had <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> wherein he had uſed ſome of the Apoſtates as inſtruments: Alſo the many <hi>Flattering Titles,</hi> and wicked <hi>Addreſſes</hi> that were afterwards given and made, firſt to <hi>Cromwel</hi> the great <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> and then to his <hi>Son,</hi> by the <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the (formerly <hi>Famous</hi> and <hi>Victorious,</hi> but now <hi>Revolting,</hi> and <hi>Time-ſerving) Army,</hi> and by many of the <hi>Churches</hi> and eminent <hi>Church-Officers</hi> and <hi>Members,</hi> yea by the generality of all <hi>Sorts</hi> and <hi>Rankes</hi> of Men, (except <hi>a poor deſpiſed Remnant,</hi> that were mourning over, and witneſſing for the precious <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt</hi>) the many printed <hi>Books,</hi> and <hi>Papers</hi> that are ſtill extant, do abundantly ſhew.</p>
            <p>I ſhall forbear to add, but come to the <hi>Second Ground,</hi> to ſhew, <hi>That the Work of the Fifth Kingdom is begun,</hi> and as theſe Workes that have been done: So in the <hi>Second place,</hi> the extraordinary way by which it hath been effected, may diſcover it to be the very <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom.</hi> This <hi>VVork</hi> (according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) being to be known by the extraordinary appearances of God in it, It is called <hi>The Kingdom which the God of Heaven ſhall ſet up,</hi> Dan. 2.44. and thoſe that <hi>ſpeak of the Glory,</hi> muſt alſo <hi>talk of the Power of this Kingdom,</hi> Pſa. 145.11. by which <hi>Power,</hi> I underſtand the extraordinary appearance of God in accompliſhing the Work of ſetting up the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> as in the coming up out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> ſo in this <hi>VVork</hi> God will ſhew, and do, great and marvelous things, <hi>Micha</hi> 7.18. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.21. and very many Scriptures ſpeak after this manner. Now that the Work in this <hi>Iſland</hi> hath been ſo done, even by an extraordinary <hi>Hand,</hi> or <hi>Power:</hi> look back as far as the old <hi>Puritant</hi> day, in which the <hi>Power of God</hi> was eminently ſeen in preſerving them, and owning their <hi>Faith, and Prayer,</hi> to the overthrowing that great <hi>Mountaine</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the reſt of that <hi>Antichriſtian, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſcopal</hi> Traine, that were imbodyed with them, and the <hi>Calling</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> upon the coming in of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and then come down to the War betwixt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> The <hi>King</hi> having the greateſt part of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry, VViſdom, Riches,</hi> old Souldiery, and <hi>Commonalty</hi> of the Nation with him, and how inconſiderable the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and their <hi>Forces</hi> were to him; But though the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> lay as it were under ground (or like a <hi>Wheele within the Wheele,</hi> hard to be diſcerned, or like <hi>David</hi> whilſt in <hi>Sauls</hi> Army) yet it being the <hi>Work</hi> that God was about to do, in this <hi>latter day,</hi> did carry the day in Great Power; and though men had their various deſigns, yet God had his deſign alſo: and both in the ſame act. Several ſuch inſtances there are in the Scripture, as the Selling of <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>Egypt, Gen.</hi> 45.5. with Chap. 56. 20. So in the Crucifying of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and divers of the like paſſages that might be named. And then come to the <hi>New Moddel</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> in the year 1645. Firſt, by what an eminent hand was that matter carryed in the <hi>Houſe</hi> againſt the very Spirit of both <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:192321:17"/>
and <hi>Nation. Secondly,</hi> how was it carried alſo againſt the very Spirit of the <hi>Army,</hi> ſeverall hundreds of the <hi>Officers</hi> were turned out, and ſome that were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eminent; and in their Roomes, were put poor Inferiour, inconſiderable perſons, who were prefer'd upon the account of their being ſuch as <hi>Feared the Lord,</hi> (that being then the received principle, to imploy men in places of truſt that feared the Lord) from which day there was a very eminent and powerfull preſence of God in and with the <hi>Army;</hi> Time would faile me to inſiſt upon the particulars to ſhew how God appeared in an extraordinary way at <hi>Naſeby Fight,</hi> and the eminent Victories obteined in the <hi>VVeſt,</hi> and in the <hi>North</hi> parts of the Nation, after the <hi>new Modell.</hi> Then come to the Second Warr when <hi>Hambleton</hi> came into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, Conſiſting of near 27000 men; alſo how God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apeared in an extraordinary way in the Victories obteined in <hi>Kent,</hi> and in <hi>VVales</hi> and at <hi>Preſton,</hi> and <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> at moſt or all which places the Enemy in number was three to one againſt us; Alſo the Eminent Hand of God in the Service in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> when that Nation was almoſt ſwallowed up by the Enemy, God appeared with an <hi>out-ſtretched arme, and wrought for his holy name;</hi> In the next place come to the Warr with <hi>Scotland</hi> which was Stated and undertaken upon <hi>Chriſt's Account,</hi> in which Warr God made his <hi>power to be known;</hi> when our Army was brought very low in a ſtrange Nation, and Compaſſed in by the Eenemy, with an Army of about 27000 beſides the whole Nation on their ſide: and we haveing a poor, weak, ſickly <hi>Army,</hi> ſcarce <hi>Nine Thouſand</hi> that were in a Capacity of fighting, then did God appear <hi>in the Mount;</hi> and in a ſhort time after the <hi>Army, Nation,</hi> and <hi>Garriſons</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> by an <hi>out-ſtretched Arme of the Lord</hi> were brought under; I forbear to mention how God broke the deſigne of the <hi>Scots King,</hi> and his <hi>Army,</hi> when they were forced to quit <hi>Scotland,</hi> and with high ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of great things from this Nation, (who like <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.6.19. are generally very eager for a <hi>King</hi>) came to <hi>VVorceſter</hi> and there were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; Then come to the Eminent Hand of God that was ſeen (as formerly) in the <hi>Garbleing:</hi> ſo now in the <hi>Breaking</hi> and <hi>Rooting</hi> up the <hi>Old Parliament</hi> with the very <hi>Foundation</hi> of their <hi>Conſtitution</hi> which was the laſt part of the <hi>Image Government;</hi> And though the <hi>VVork</hi> of the Lord was carried on before under that <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet it muſt alſo break them, as they were a part of the <hi>Horne. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> after he was firſt <hi>Anointed</hi> did <hi>fight the Battels</hi> in <hi>Sauls</hi> Army, and as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, ſo the power of God was Eminently with him in the work; but afterwards <hi>Davids Kingdome</hi> was exalted over <hi>Sauls Kingdome,</hi> and brake down his <hi>Houſe,</hi> for ſo had God ſpoken, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.28. that the <hi>Kingdome ſhould be taken from Saul;</hi> And <hi>Saul</hi> knew that <hi>ſo long as the Son of Jeſſe was upon the ground,</hi> his <hi>Kingdome</hi> could <hi>not be eſtabliſhed,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.31. This is to be noted that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.7. had the preheminence of <hi>Saul</hi> in the <hi>Battells,</hi> even whilſt he fought in <hi>Sauls Army;</hi> Now that <hi>Old Parliament</hi> being broken upon the <hi>Account</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> that his <hi>Government</hi> might <hi>take place:</hi> by this breach an end was put to the <hi>Nationall Constitution,</hi> or to any <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> that might ariſe from the <hi>Nation</hi> as a <hi>Nation,</hi> but the right is brought to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is, for he is <hi>King of Nations,</hi> and (under him) it is <hi>given to the Saints,</hi> who <hi>muſt poſſeſs the Kingdome, Dan.</hi> 7.27.18. and therefore it is no wonder
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192321:18"/>
that all this time of the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> could make nothing <hi>Riſe</hi> from the <hi>Nationall Conſtitution,</hi> or if they did, could not make it <hi>Stand up,</hi> but it hath been like a man when his life is gone from him, and the <hi>Day of the Lord</hi> according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.16. hath been <hi>upon all their pleaſant Pictures.</hi> Then come to the <hi>VVar</hi> with <hi>Holland,</hi> and call over the Records which do abundantly manifeſt how eminently God <hi>Wrought</hi> and made his <hi>Wonders</hi> to be known in the <hi>Deeps,</hi> yea <hi>both VVind and Sea obeyed him</hi> in that Warr. As to the Eminent Hand of God in the <hi>Call</hi> of that <hi>Little Aſſembly, I</hi> ſhall not ſpeak of it in this place, having ſpoken to it in the Firſt Ground; but upon the whole I may conclude this Second Ground with theſe Scriptures, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.23. <hi>According to this time it ſhall be ſaid of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>what hath God wrought?</hi> compared with, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.4. &amp; 107.8. &amp; 111.4. alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.1. <hi>that his name is neere his wonderous works declare.</hi> And though this Generation as <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.9. <hi>have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the things that their eyes have ſeen:</hi> yet God in much mercy makes theſe <hi>Wonderfull Works</hi> as pretious food to a poor <hi>Deſpiſed Remnant,</hi> that are witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, and waiting for the Reſurrection of the Glorious <hi>Cauſe of Christ. Pſal.</hi> 74.14 &amp; 111.2, 3, 4. Compared with <hi>v.</hi> 5. Pſal. 46.8. <hi>Come behold the works of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c: Hoſ. 14.9. <hi>who ſo is wiſe, and he ſhall underſtand theſe things,</hi> &amp;c: Iſay. 51.9, 10. <hi>Awake, Awake O Arme of the Lord, as in Ancient dayes, art not thou it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Ground</hi> which may further manifeſt that the <hi>Work</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> hath taken place, is, from the <hi>Cauſe</hi> that was <hi>Stated,</hi> and <hi>Layed</hi> in the <hi>Bottom</hi> as the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of the Quarrell, upon which the great <hi>Works</hi> have been wrought, and Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries obtained: and that hath been the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and as the <hi>Day,</hi> ſo the <hi>Light</hi> hath increaſed; <hi>Firſt,</hi> againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy,</hi> not only againſt their wicked practices, but againſt the Foundation of their ſtanding, as <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> and though there was then but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Light in the viſible <hi>Kingdome of Chriſt,</hi> yet there was ſo much as the Lord ſaw needfull for that day. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in the beginning of the Wars, which outwardly to men appeared to be betwixt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> but in the <hi>Bottom</hi> (as thoſe who had the <hi>Light</hi> of that <hi>Day</hi> may remember) was betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt;</hi> and many of the people of God took up Armes in <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> upon the account of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and went <hi>to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> although it was but a dark Day, and a <hi>day of ſmall things;</hi> But by that time we came to the Warr with <hi>Scotland,</hi> there was a good meaſure of <hi>Kingdome Light</hi> given down, and ſprung up, though it was not upon all that were engaged in the <hi>War,</hi> but only ſome few to whom the Lord was pleaſed to manifeſt it; and through this <hi>Light</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> came more clearly to be ſtated in publique view, and then the ground upon which the late <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Monarchy</hi> was taken off, is publickly aſſerted by the <hi>Army,</hi> (who were the moſt eminent outward <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in the <hi>Work</hi>) to be upon the account of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as may appeare by a <hi>Letter</hi> from the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> at their march for <hi>Scotland,</hi> directed to the reſt of the <hi>Army</hi> that remained at their <hi>Quarters</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and alſo by their <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> when they were come to <hi>Muſcleborough</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi> This <hi>Cauſe</hi> comes yet more clearly to be <hi>Stated,</hi> and <hi>Owned</hi> in the <hi>Breach</hi> of the <hi>Old Parliament,</hi> and is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192321:18"/>
laid in the Bottom (by thoſe that were <hi>Anointed</hi> for, and had the <hi>Light</hi> of that day) as the <hi>Ground</hi> upon which they were <hi>Broken,</hi> and alſo as a farther manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this, <hi>the Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> being to take place next to the <hi>Image Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and that being broken, the <hi>Little Aſſembly</hi> was called, and the <hi>Government</hi> delivered to them upon the <hi>Avowed Account of the Son of God;</hi> Alſo in the Stating and Carrying on the War with <hi>Holland,</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> for the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in that War, was (by thoſe that had the <hi>Light</hi>) upon the account of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> theſe things are evident and may further appear by a <hi>Letter</hi> from the Officers <hi>at Whitehall</hi> to Lt. Gen. <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> and the reſt of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in <hi>Ireland</hi> upon the Breach of the <hi>Old Parliament,</hi> and alſo by <hi>Cromwels Speech</hi> to the <hi>Little Aſſembly</hi> ſhewing their Call to be <hi>upon the account of Chriſt;</hi> and alſo the proceedings of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> and the Committee <hi>of Admiralty</hi> in the managing of that War with <hi>Holland;</hi> The <hi>Letter</hi> to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>Letter</hi> (before mentioned) to thoſe of the <hi>Army</hi> that remained in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the <hi>Muſcleborough Declaration,</hi> and <hi>Cromwels Speech,</hi> are all Printed together in the <hi>Book</hi> before-mentioned called The <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> in <hi>oppoſition to the Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> and is Sold at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Popes-Head Ally.</hi> The Grounds upon which the enlightned Part of the <hi>Little Aſſembly</hi> did Act, and Own their ſitting do alſo clear the <hi>Cauſe</hi> to to be ſtated for <hi>Chriſt</hi> againſt <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth Ground</hi> to clear this <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> is from the <hi>Anointing,</hi> a Meaſure whereof hath been given down in, &amp; for the accompliſhing of the <hi>Work</hi> &amp; by which it hath been done. And <hi>firſt</hi> that there is an <hi>Anointing</hi> reſerved for, and promiſed to this <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> yea that the <hi>Work</hi> is to be done by the <hi>Anointing</hi> (though not without the uſe of <hi>Inſtruments</hi>) conſider <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.27. which ſpeaking of the <hi>Latter day Work,</hi> and of <hi>Zions deliverance,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the yoke ſhall be broken off becauſe of the Anointing</hi> alſo <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.6. ſpeaking of this <hi>VVork</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Lord ſhall be for a Spirit of Judgement to them that ſit in Judgement, and for ſtrength to them that turn the Battel to the Gate.</hi> Alſo <hi>Haggai</hi> 2.5. <hi>My Spirit remaineth among you fear ye not;</hi> though this word in the Letter may relate to the <hi>Building</hi> of the <hi>Temple;</hi> yet that <hi>VVork</hi> being Typical to this <hi>Glorious VVork</hi> of the <hi>Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day,</hi> this <hi>promiſe</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> doth moſt properly reſpect this <hi>Latter day VVork;</hi> So Zech. 4.6. <hi>Not by might, nor by Power but by my Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. The word (upon the forementioned ground) may alſo be applyed to this <hi>VVork</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> Iſai. 59.19.21. <hi>when the enemy ſhall come in like a flood the Spirit of the Lord ſhall put him to flight,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe and ſeveral other Scriptures do clear it, that this <hi>VVork</hi> hath the <hi>promiſe of the Spirit</hi> in a ſpecial manner belonging to it; and now that a meaſure of this <hi>Spirit</hi> hath been given down for <hi>Light, wiſdom, ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>courage</hi> in the <hi>Work</hi> which hath been done amongſt us, hath been very evident to, and owned by many who have been employed therein, and alſo to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Beholders, yea God hath wreſted, a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to the truth of this out of the <hi>mouths</hi> of the very <hi>enemies</hi> themſelves, and although (through the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi>) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have loſt that ſpirit, the <hi>Anointing,</hi> being gone of from them, (as it went from <hi>Saul</hi> through his wickedneſs) yet through <hi>unſpeakable grace,</hi> there are ſome who (being yet preſerved for the <hi>King</hi>) have ſtill a <hi>meaſure</hi> of it remaining with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192321:19"/>
them; Many things might be inſtanced to ſhew that there was of this <hi>Anointing</hi> given down in the <hi>VVork</hi> which did help the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> over the many <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> of <hi>difficulties,</hi> and <hi>oppoſitions</hi> that ſtood in the way, and through this, the <hi>enemy</hi> was much daunted and their <hi>VViſdom,</hi> and <hi>Councels</hi> confounded and <hi>turned into fooliſhneſs,</hi> and made to them like the <hi>Councels of Achitophel,</hi> and this through <hi>poor, weak,</hi> and <hi>contemptible Inſtruments;</hi> this ſpirit did not onely <hi>reſt</hi> upon ſome of the <hi>leading Perſons</hi> and others of the <hi>Army:</hi> but upon many of the <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who were by <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> made as <hi>Princes</hi> in the <hi>VVork;</hi> But I ſhall leave this to the Conſciences of thoſe who in the <hi>fear of the Lord</hi> may look back to <hi>the things that their eyes have ſeen,</hi> and call to mind <hi>the days of old,</hi> which may ſpeak much more to them (if <hi>their conſciences</hi> through the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> be not <hi>ceared</hi>) then I am able to expreſſe.</p>
            <p>But it is objected, that <hi>if they ever had had the Anointing it would have remained upon them, but ſeveral of them have proved Apoſtates, and diſcovered themſelves to be wicked men, yea the moſt eminent Leaders in the VVork;</hi> and this proves a <hi>ſtumbling block</hi> to ſome of the Lords precious People, who are ready to conclude and ſay (as to this <hi>VVork) that the Lord is not among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a Twofold <hi>Anointing,</hi> the one peculiar to <hi>true Believers,</hi> by which they are <hi>convinced of ſin,</hi> and enabled to <hi>believe on Chriſt</hi> for the ſalvation of their ſouls, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit is Faith; The Second</hi> is proper to thoſe whom the <hi>Lord Calls,</hi> and imployes in ſome peculiar or extraordinary <hi>VVork,</hi> either for <hi>Propheſie,</hi> as <hi>Num</hi> 24.2. <hi>The Spirit of God came upon Balaam;</hi> Or for <hi>War</hi> as <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.34. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord came upon or clothed Gideon;</hi> The like of <hi>Sampſon Judg.</hi> 14.19. Or for the execution of <hi>Juſtice, Judgement,</hi> and <hi>Vengeance</hi> upon the enemies of the Lord, as that of <hi>Jehu,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. and tenth Chapters; Or for ſome ſpecial <hi>Building VVork</hi> as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 45.1. Compare 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.23. <hi>Cyrus</hi> is called Gods <hi>Anointed,</hi> alſo <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.3.6. Or for <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> ſo it was upon <hi>Saul,</hi> and through ſin (as before was men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) came off from him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13.14. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord departed</hi> from <hi>Saul, and came upon David,</hi> and <hi>an evil ſpirit</hi> was upon <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Second</hi> part of the <hi>Anointing</hi> under the <hi>ſeveral Heads</hi> of it before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, may be upon <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and men in their <hi>natural Eſtate,</hi> as by <hi>Balaam, Saul, Jehu,</hi> and others may appear, and this <hi>Anointing</hi> may either depart or be taken from them through ſin or when the <hi>VVork</hi> for which it was given is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
            <p>The Firſt part of the <hi>Anoineing</hi> where ever it is in truth received, though through ſin it may be <hi>grieved, quenched,</hi> and the <hi>operation</hi> of it not diſcerned, and the <hi>comforts</hi> of it much taken away, yet it remains as <hi>a well of water ſpringing up into everlaſting Life,</hi> Joh. 4.14. chap. 14.16. and if this <hi>diſtinction</hi> in the <hi>Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> be obſerved, and rightly underſtood, it will not be accounted an owning of that corrupt Principle of <hi>Falling from grace:</hi> to ſay, <hi>That by the Apoſtacy,</hi> the <hi>ſpirit is departed from ſuch who were anointed for, and uſed in the VVork which the Lord hath done among us;</hi> and it is no wonder to behold at this day, that many of the people of God in the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> have <hi>loſt their ſtrength</hi> through the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and as <hi>Sampſon</hi> without <hi>his locks,</hi> are become <hi>like other men,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:192321:19"/>
though they themſelves cannot ſee it; yea how did the <hi>Great Men</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> (who were formerly very <hi>famous</hi> for <hi>Zeal,</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi>) manifeſt themſelves to be like <hi>men of might</hi> who had <hi>loſt their hands,</hi> and like <hi>Princes</hi> whoſe <hi>ſpirits were cut off,</hi> (Pſal. 76.5.12.) when the pretended <hi>Old Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> returnd to their <hi>Uſurpation</hi> at <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> and if this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>Anointing</hi> be kept to, it may fully anſwer the objection; And though it ſhould be concluded that <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and divers others imployed in the <hi>VVork,</hi> were without the <hi>truth of grace</hi> in their <hi>ſouls</hi> (which thing I leave to the Lord) yet it cannot follow from thence that the <hi>VVork</hi> they were imployed in, was not the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> for as hath been ſhewed, God doth ſometimes <hi>Call</hi> and <hi>Anoint</hi> unconverted perſons to his <hi>Work.</hi> It is ſaid of wicked <hi>Jehu</hi> 2 Kings 10.30. <hi>That he did well, and did that which was right in Gods eyes,</hi> yea and <hi>according to all that was in Gods heart;</hi> therefore it may not be ſaid, that the <hi>Work</hi> was not the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or that <hi>Cromwell</hi> was not <hi>Anointed</hi> for that <hi>Work</hi> becauſe he <hi>ſo wickedly turned aſide,</hi> and dyed in his <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> Nay the Lord may <hi>avenge</hi> the very <hi>blood</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> with his <hi>Nobles,</hi> and <hi>that wicked Generation,</hi> upon the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> of <hi>his Army,</hi> together with the very <hi>Congregations</hi> that have <hi>turned aſide with them in,</hi> and not Witneſſed againſt the <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> Though this may be accounted raſh Judgment, yet it will be no more then is ſaid in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 1.4. concerning the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>Ahab, For yet a little while ſaith the Lord, and I will avenge the blood of Jezreel</hi> (to wit, the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Ahab,</hi> which were ſlain by <hi>Jehu</hi> in <hi>Jezreel,</hi> 2 Kings 11.30. and Chap. 10.11.) <hi>Upon the Houſe of Jehu,</hi> ſo that God accounts <hi>Jehu</hi> guilty of the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Ahabs Houſe,</hi> which muſt needs be through the wickedneſs of <hi>Jehu:</hi> the <hi>Judgment of the Lord</hi> executed by him upon the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Ahab,</hi> being righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Let the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> to whom this may come, <hi>Read,</hi> and <hi>Tremble,</hi> at <hi>this VVord,</hi> and let them not think that they <hi>ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> if God come to <hi>avenge the blood</hi> (which hath been ſhed in the late quarrel) <hi>upon them</hi> that have ſo <hi>turned from</hi> and <hi>denyed</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of Christ,</hi> which is the only ground to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all our proceedings, in knocking off the <hi>Horne of the Beast</hi> in this <hi>Iſland;</hi> and though <hi>Cromwell</hi> in all the <hi>Work</hi> that he did might ſeek his own ends, and keep his <hi>Idolls</hi> in his heart, Yet that will not leſſen the force of this Argument (to wit) <hi>That the Yoak hath been bro en becauſe of the anointing;</hi> if the proceedings of <hi>Jehu</hi> in the <hi>Lords Work</hi> be conſulted, we may find much of that in him, to wit, <hi>ſeeking himſelf,</hi> and <hi>keeping his Idolls,</hi> 2 Kings 10.31. I ſhall not ſpeak further of that extraordinary <hi>Anointing,</hi> which was upon <hi>Cromwell</hi> and many others, in <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, Army</hi> and <hi>Navy,</hi> by which they were carryed forth above, and beyond their own Spirits in the <hi>Work,</hi> which makes it very evident that the <hi>Work</hi> hath been done, not by the <hi>Might</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> but by the <hi>Spirit of the Lord,</hi> though all that were employed in the <hi>Work</hi> had not the <hi>Anointing;</hi> Not all that were with <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>VVork,</hi> but <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>VVorthies,</hi> with ſome others had the <hi>Anointing</hi> for it; All the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> had not the <hi>Anointing,</hi> to <hi>underſtand the times,</hi> but it reſted with the <hi>Heads</hi> of them who had <hi>all their Brethren at their Command,</hi> 1 Chro. 12.32. from theſe and divers other inſtances, it may appear,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:192321:20"/>
that the ordinary way of the Lord hath not been to <hi>Anoint</hi> all, but only ſome of them that have been imployed in his great <hi>VVork.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth Ground</hi> to prove that the <hi>Work</hi> hath taken place in this Nation, may be taken from the many <hi>Revolutions</hi> and <hi>Overturnings</hi> that have attended all the pretended <hi>Governments,</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> that have been in this <hi>Nation,</hi> ſince the interruption of the exerciſe of the <hi>Government of Chriſt</hi> in the hands of his <hi>People</hi> in the <hi>Little Aſſembly</hi> before mentioned; It is evident that they have been ſuch <hi>Revolutions</hi> as have not been known in former days, though few conſiders the Cauſe of it; There have none come up upon the <hi>Stage</hi> to <hi>Uſurp</hi> the <hi>Power,</hi> that haue gone off without a brand upon them of Gods diſpleaſure. Now that ſuch things muſt be when the <hi>Day of the Lord,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> takes place in the World; Conſider, Firſt, that word in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. ſpeaking of the <hi>Day</hi> in which the <hi>Lord alone ſhall be exalted,</hi> which muſt reſpect the <hi>Day</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſaith in Verſe 16. <hi>The day of the Lord ſhall be upon every pleaſant picture,</hi> which I underſtand to be thoſe pretended <hi>Governments,</hi> which ſhall be <hi>Set up,</hi> when the great <hi>Powers,</hi> or the <hi>Image Government</hi> is broken; and further in Verſe 18. <hi>the Idols ſhall be utterly aboliſhed;</hi> which as I underſtand reſpects the ſame with Verſe 16; It muſt be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that many <hi>pleaſant Pictures</hi> and <hi>Idols</hi> have been ſet up ſince the <hi>Apostacy</hi> in this Nation, and it is moſt evident that <hi>the Day of the Lord</hi> hath been <hi>upon them,</hi> and like that in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.9.10. the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> have <hi>Aſſociated,</hi> and <hi>Guirded</hi> themſelves <hi>and taken Counſel,</hi> but all hath come to nothing except <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> upon themſelves. The Spirit ſpeaking <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.9. of <hi>the Latter day VVork</hi> when the <hi>Stones of the Altar muſt be broken a ſunder:</hi> holds forth, that there muſt be <hi>Groves,</hi> and <hi>Images,</hi> and endeavours uſed to make them ſtand up; there hath been among us many <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> ſince the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> but that Word hath been fulfilled, that <hi>they ſhall not ſtand up,</hi> and though the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> have been <hi>ſeeking deep to hide their Councels from the Lord,</hi> yet the <hi>VViſdom and Underſtanding of their VViſemen.</hi> hath been <hi>hid</hi> &amp; <hi>periſhed,</hi> and their <hi>turning of things upſide down,</hi> hath been <hi>eſteemed as the Potters Clay,</hi> Iſa. 29.14, 15, 16. The <hi>Throne</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> being given to <hi>Christ,</hi> is become too heavy for the <hi>Apostates</hi> to bear, but they ſinke and wither under it.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown how <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his <hi>Family</hi> ſunk under it: they were <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> and <hi>weaker</hi> from the firſt day they came to the <hi>Throne,</hi> till it was taken away from them; the like of the Reliques of the <hi>Old Parliament,</hi> who though they came in with a high hand, yet ſoon withered and came to nothing but ſcorn and deriſion, the like of the <hi>Army</hi> and their pretended <hi>Committee of Safety,</hi> and for theſe that are now returned, and in the <hi>Uſurpation</hi> of the <hi>Throne,</hi> and have the very <hi>ſpirit of the Nation</hi> with them, I do not doubt, however they may carry it with a high hand, but they ſhall ſhortly <hi>melt like wax before the fire,</hi> and ſhall be as <hi>ſmoak driven away,</hi> and made <hi>as Aſhes under the Soles of the feet</hi> of thoſe that <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Wait</hi> in a true ſpirit for the Reſurrection of <hi>Chriſts Righteous Cauſe,</hi> though the Lord may for a time ſuffer them, yea and make them as the <hi>Aſſyrian Rod</hi> to execute the <hi>Stroke</hi> that is comming upon the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of <hi>this Generation</hi> for their <hi>Diſowning, Denying,</hi> yea and <hi>Crucifying</hi> the <hi>Righteous Cauſe</hi> of their <hi>dear
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:192321:20"/>
King,</hi> who through the <hi>ſhedding of his Blood</hi> for them, deſerved other things at their hands.</p>
            <p>I ſhall preſent one Scripture more to this <hi>Fifth Ground,</hi> to wit <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. <hi>The Kingdome ſhall not be left to other people.</hi> The words do hold forth Two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That other people then Saints ſhall make attempts upon, and endeavour to take,</hi> and keep this Kingdom after it hath taken place in the hands of the <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though other people may endeavour to <hi>take</hi> and <hi>poſſeſs it,</hi> yet it ſhall not <hi>be left to them,</hi> or they ſhall not enjoy or poſſeſs it, as the other <hi>Foure Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> that went before this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which were <hi>left to other people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees</hi> was left to the <hi>Medes and Perſians,</hi> and their Monarchy to the <hi>Graecians,</hi> and the <hi>Graecians</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> ſhall be left to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt, whoſe Kingdome ſhall never be deſtroyed</hi> nor <hi>left to other people;</hi> and it is manifeſt that ſince this <hi>Kingdom</hi> hath taken place in the hands of the <hi>Saints, Other People</hi> have endeavoured and made great attempts to <hi>Take</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſs it:</hi> as <hi>Cromwell,</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> the Reliques of the <hi>Old Parliament</hi> which God hath at ſeverall times <hi>Caſt out,</hi> and it is as cleare that the <hi>Kingdom</hi> hath not <hi>been,</hi> neither is, <hi>left</hi> to any of them; and though the <hi>Family</hi> of the <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arts</hi> whom God hath poured <hi>Contempt upon and Broken,</hi> have alſo endeavoured to <hi>take the Kingdome,</hi> and for ought I know may come as neere to <hi>Obtaine</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſs</hi> it as <hi>Cromwell</hi> or any of the forementioned <hi>Uſurpers</hi> have done; yet let them know, that the <hi>VVord of the Lord</hi> ſhall ſtand, and <hi>the Kingdome ſhall not be left to Other People</hi> then the <hi>Saints,</hi> who by grace are kept for <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> with <hi>the VVord of their Teſtimony,</hi> are helped to undermine, and bring down all the <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Images,</hi> which the <hi>Treacherous Dealers</hi> have ſet up.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sixth Ground</hi> to prove that the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdome</hi> hath taken place, is from the <hi>Eminent hand</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that hath been ſeen in preſerving the lives of thoſe which have been kept by <hi>Grace</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> in a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> againſt thoſe that have <hi>turned aſide</hi> from, and <hi>betray'd</hi> his <hi>Righteous Cauſe.</hi> It is not unknown that ever ſince the Firſt day of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> the Lord hath had a <hi>Remnant</hi> which he hath kept, &amp; helped to <hi>Favour</hi> &amp; <hi>Cleave</hi> to the <hi>Pretious</hi> though deſpiſed <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and by them a <hi>Publick Witneſs</hi> hath been kept up againſt the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and there hath been many <hi>Gins,</hi> and <hi>Snares laid,</hi> and <hi>Trappans</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to take them, and Old <hi>Acts</hi> revived and publiſhed, by which their <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſhould be <hi>adjudged Treaſon,</hi> Severall of the <hi>Faithfull Remnant</hi> having been <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> and <hi>Impriſoned,</hi> and deep <hi>Deſignes</hi> and <hi>Plots</hi> laid to take away their lives, the <hi>Great Apostates</hi> having even been <hi>thirſting</hi> for their <hi>Blood:</hi> but ſuch hath been the Wiſdome and Over-ruleing hand of <hi>God,</hi> that to this day all their <hi>Plots</hi> have been diſappointed, and not one of the <hi>Remnant</hi> hath ſuffered to the loſs of <hi>Life</hi> by them: and though thoſe now in <hi>Power,</hi> or ſome that may <hi>Succeed them</hi> may be permitted to come ſo high as to take away the <hi>Lives</hi> of many of <hi>Gods people,</hi> as a judgment from the <hi>Lord</hi> upon them for their <hi>turning aſide</hi> from the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>joyning in affinity with,</hi> and <hi>pertaking of the Sins of Babylon,</hi> yet ſurely the <hi>Lord</hi> that hath hitherto, will ſtill preſerve the lives of his <hi>Faithfull Remnant</hi> whom he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192321:21"/>
ſhall pleaſe to keep for his <hi>Son</hi> in this evil day; In former days the lives of Gods faithfull ones were taken away by the Enemies, when according to their own Laws they could not lay ſo much to their <hi>Charge</hi> as may be <hi>Charged</hi> upon the <hi>Remnant</hi> at this day, who according to the <hi>VVicked Lawes</hi> may be adjudged guilty of the Higheſt <hi>Treaſon</hi> in <hi>VVitneſſing</hi> for, and <hi>Proclaiming Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the <hi>Uſurpers,</hi> and yet their lives have been, and ſtill are preſerved; and the reaſon I underſtand, is not that theſe <hi>Uſurpers</hi> are better then the <hi>Cruell Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors</hi> in former days, but they being in that day when <hi>Babylon</hi> was <hi>filling</hi> up <hi>her meaſure,</hi> and making <hi>her ſelf Drunk with the Blood of the Saints,</hi> and theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> after <hi>Babylons Cup was full,</hi> and the <hi>Vengance of the Lord</hi> by the <hi>pouring out of his Vialls</hi> being begun upon her, though the former were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to perſecute the <hi>Faithfull People of God</hi> to death, yet theſe are not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo to do, becauſe the <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> is altered: and this <hi>Work</hi> having taken place, though great <hi>Tryalls</hi> and <hi>Deaths</hi> are come upon it, and a great <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from it: yet the <hi>Lord</hi> ſuffers not the <hi>Work</hi> to be ſo farr turned back as that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould <hi>drink</hi> any more of <hi>Zions Blood,</hi> the ſtreame being now turned upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> but if Gods people <hi>abide in,</hi> and <hi>ſhare</hi> of <hi>Babylons ſins,</hi> let them not think that becauſe they are the <hi>People of God</hi> they ſhall eſcape <hi>her Plagues,</hi> Rev. 18.4. And though <hi>Zion</hi> muſt <hi>reward Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>Vialls</hi> muſt <hi>come forth</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> yet the <hi>Lord</hi> for wiſe ends, and beſt known to himſelf may permit the moſt <hi>VVicked</hi> and <hi>groſſer part of Babylon</hi> to <hi>execute</hi> that part <hi>of the Vengance,</hi> that is to come upon ſuch of his <hi>Own People,</hi> who remaine in <hi>and pertake of Babylons ſins,</hi> &amp; thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his <hi>Own People</hi> from doing that part of the <hi>VVork</hi> which might be unpleaſant to them.</p>
            <p>There are many <hi>Objections</hi> made againſt this Truth (to wit) <hi>That the Work of the Fifth Kingdome is begun,</hi> ſome of them I have already occaſionally ſpoken to in the forementioned <hi>Grounds;</hi> But the great <hi>Stumbling Block</hi> that lyeth in the way of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, is the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from, and ſo the <hi>Death</hi> that is come upon this <hi>VVork</hi> which makes them ready to ſay with the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Luke 24.21. <hi>VVe truſted it had been he,</hi> &amp;c. When this <hi>Cauſe</hi> was publickly own'd by the Lord in the <hi>High places of the Field,</hi> there were many that would cry <hi>Hoſanna to the Son of David;</hi> and with much rejoyceing imbrace his <hi>Cauſe;</hi> but ſince a <hi>Death</hi> is come upon it, the <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of the true <hi>Favourers</hi> that publickly own it, is become very <hi>Small.</hi> When <hi>Chriſt</hi> was upon the <hi>Earth in the Days of His Fleſh, ſhewing and doing great Signes and VVonders,</hi> there were many own'd and follow'd him; but when he comes to the <hi>Judgment, Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> very few continued with him: ſeverall emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Diſciples</hi> were ſtumbled <hi>not underſtanding the Scriptures,</hi> till <hi>Chriſt</hi> being <hi>riſen</hi> comes and <hi>opens</hi> them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24, 25, 26, 27.45. 46, and as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> in that, ſo many of the <hi>Profeſſing Generation</hi> in this day, are through ignorance ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, not underſtanding, or at leaſt not ſo conſidering that after the <hi>Fifth King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> hath taken place in the world, there muſt be ſuch an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from, and <hi>Death</hi> upon it; Now if there be an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from a <hi>VVork,</hi> the <hi>VVork</hi> muſt needs take place before the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> without which there could be no ſuch <hi>Apostacy,</hi> That there muſt be ſuch a <hi>Revolting from, and Death</hi> upon <hi>the Work</hi> of this <hi>Fifth Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:192321:21"/>Conſider, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſeveral <hi>Types</hi> thereof contained in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> as <hi>Iſraels</hi> coming out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> in which were many <hi>Revoltings, Turnings</hi> back, and <hi>Deaths</hi> upon the <hi>Work:</hi> yea <hi>Forty Years</hi> was the <hi>Tryal</hi> upon them, before they came to <hi>Canaan,</hi> and for ought we can find from the Scriptures, the Lord had not before given them warning, or told them of this <hi>Death</hi> in the <hi>Wildernes,</hi> though he had told them exactly how long they ſhould be in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and given them great grounds for ſence to ſay, <hi>Is the Lord among us?</hi> and many might cry out (as at this day) <hi>What Scripture ground is there to believe, that ſuch a Death ſhould come upon the Work of the Kingdom?</hi> and if we had no more ground then we find <hi>Iſrael</hi> had to expect ſuch a <hi>Death;</hi> yet as it was theirs, ſo it would be our ſin, after ſuch wonderful <hi>Works</hi> of God as he hath <hi>wrought</hi> among us, to ſay as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Is the Lord amongſt us?</hi> or <hi>hath the Lord begun to bring us to the promiſed glory?</hi> though God had wrought many wonderful <hi>VVorks</hi> in the ſight of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, yet <hi>they underſtood not his wonders;</hi> no doubt but they knew that ſuch things were done, but they underſtood not the great <hi>Deſign</hi> of God in them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.7.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Typical example,</hi> is from <hi>Davids Kingdom,</hi> which did clearly <hi>Type</hi> out this <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> according to <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.32. If we read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. to 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. we may find many <hi>Deaths</hi> upon the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>Davids Kingdom</hi> after it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; Firſt whilſt he was purſued by <hi>Saul,</hi> and then after <hi>Sauls</hi> death he obtains but one <hi>Tribe</hi> to follow him for Seven years and ſix Moneths, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.11. There was War betwixt him and the <hi>Houſe of Saul</hi> long after <hi>Sauls</hi> death, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.1. and in moſt of the time of that <hi>Seven years War,</hi> his <hi>Kingdom</hi> was under a great <hi>Death;</hi> alſo there came a great <hi>Death</hi> upon his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> when his ſon <hi>Abſalom</hi> conſpired againſt him, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> fled from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which was the <hi>Kings Seat,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.16.17. Chapters.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Typical example,</hi> is <hi>Iſraels</hi> return from the 70. <hi>years captivity in Babylon,</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and their <hi>building of the Temple;</hi> great <hi>Deaths,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions</hi> did attend that <hi>Work,</hi> both from the enemies of <hi>Judah</hi> who endeavoured to block up the way, and from Gods <hi>own People</hi> who cryed the <hi>time is not yet come,</hi> though they thought it a time for themſelves to <hi>dwell in their cieled houſes;</hi> and this may be obſerved by the way, that though the enemies of <hi>Judah</hi> by force did cauſe the <hi>Work to ceaſe,</hi> yet that doth not excuſe the neglects and backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Gods People</hi> who ought to be <hi>valiant for the Truth.</hi> Theſe things contained in this third Particular, being written at large in the books of <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah, Zechariah, and Haggai,</hi> I ſhal refer you to the reading and comparing of them, and ſhall come in the next place to cite ſome Propheſies of Scripture which relate to this <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> and do clearly hold forth that there muſt be ſuch an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from, and <hi>Death</hi> upon the <hi>Work,</hi> after it hath taken place. The Firſt Scripture is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1.2.3.4.5.6. <hi>The Heathen rage, the Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take Councel together againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed, ſaying, let us break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from us,</hi> &amp;c. By the <hi>Bands</hi> and <hi>cords:</hi> I underſtand the <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the <hi>breaking in ſunder,</hi> or <hi>caſting off its Government</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> muſt needs hold
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192321:22"/>
forth a <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt, and a <hi>turning</hi> from them after they had taken place in the <hi>World,</hi> and then the Lord doth <hi>vex them</hi> by <hi>ſetting his King,</hi> &amp;c. and after this as in verſe 8.9. Chriſt muſt have the <hi>Heathen for his inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the Earth for his poſſeſſion,</hi> and muſt <hi>break them with a Rod of Iron,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The next Scripture is <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.2. <hi>O Lord revive thy Work,</hi> &amp;c. if we conſult the Scope of the words, they will appear to be a <hi>Prayer</hi> for, or a <hi>Propheſie</hi> of the <hi>Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day Work,</hi> and doth clearly hold forth a <hi>Death</hi> to come upon it after it hath been begun; alſo he ſaith, <hi>O Lord remember mercy,</hi> which ſhews that the <hi>Work</hi> and People of God at that time when this Prayer takes place, are very low; alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.15. <hi>But Judgement ſhall return unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. This word doth relate to the time of Gods coming forth in the execution of <hi>vengeance,</hi> as the ſcope of the Pſalm doth manifeſt, and to that part of the time when Gods People are low, and the enemies high, as verſe 16. <hi>Who will riſe up for me againſt the evil doers,</hi> &amp;c. alſo verſe 20.21. Now <hi>Judgement</hi> being to be underſtood) of <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and by its being with <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> (I underſtand the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> to be upon <hi>Chriſts ſhoulders,</hi> (in whom alone there is <hi>true Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi>) and in the <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> for, and under him; and by this <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> returning to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Saints:</hi> muſt imply, <hi>Firſt,</hi> that it hath already taken place; and <hi>Secondly</hi> that there is a turning, or an <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from it.</p>
            <p>There is another <hi>Great objection</hi> or <hi>ſtumbling block</hi> that I find is laid in the <hi>Way</hi> at this day about the <hi>Two VVitneſſes</hi> mentioned in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. which is this.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>That the VVitneſſes are not yet ſlain, and therefore the VVork of the Fifth Kingdom cannot be begun, neither hath the Active diſpenſation taken place, but the Saints muſt be, preparing for, and in the expectation of ſharp ſufferings, even to Corporal death as the fulfilling of their Staying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Firſt,</hi> If it ſhould be granted that the <hi>Slaying of the VVitneſſes</hi> muſt be accompliſhed in this <hi>Iſland;</hi> yet If there <hi>Two</hi> following <hi>things</hi> be conſidered, it will rather confirm the <hi>Truth,</hi> viz. that the <hi>Work is begun,</hi> then prove a <hi>Stumbling Block</hi> in the way of it, And the <hi>Firſt thing,</hi> is, what the <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> are, and what their <hi>Teſtimony</hi> is; and <hi>The Second,</hi> what their <hi>Slaying</hi> is.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, If the Scriptures be weighed, the <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> cannot be underſtood of <hi>Two</hi> particular Perſons (as ſome have ſuppoſed) becauſe they are to <hi>Propheſie</hi> a <hi>thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Dayes or Years,</hi> for the <hi>Dayes</hi> muſt be Prophetical, a <hi>Day</hi> for a <hi>Year</hi> according to <hi>Num.</hi> 14.34. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.6 All muſt grant that the <hi>Latter Number</hi> to wit, the <hi>Three Dayes and a Half</hi> mentioned in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11 9. muſt be <hi>Prophetically</hi> underſtood, and no doubt the <hi>Former</hi> muſt in that agree with the <hi>Latter</hi> and if they muſt <hi>Propheſie</hi> ſo long, they cannot be <hi>Two Perſons,</hi> for no ſuch ſingular extraordinary Perſons have yet been found in the world ſince <hi>Johns Dayes,</hi> and there is much ground from the Scripture to believe that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> which in verſe the 7. <hi>Slaves the VVitneſſes</hi> when they have finiſhed the 1260. <hi>Dayes or Years,</hi> hath not ſo much time to come of his <hi>Reign;</hi> Much more might be ſpoken Both from the <hi>VVar</hi> that is <hi>made with them,</hi> and from the <hi>Time</hi> of their <hi>Lying Dead,</hi> to ſhew that they cannot be <hi>Two Perſons,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192321:22"/>
neither can they be underſtood of the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as <hi>Two</hi> diſtinct <hi>Churches; Firſt,</hi> becauſe ever ſince <hi>Johns</hi> Dayes the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as a <hi>Church,</hi> have been <hi>cut off,</hi> and not in a capacity of bearing <hi>VVitneſs</hi> for <hi>Chriſt. Secondly</hi> when they ſhall be <hi>Called,</hi> they are not to <hi>Come</hi> in as a diſtinct <hi>Church;</hi> but both <hi>Jew,</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> being <hi>all One in Chriſt,</hi> makes but one <hi>Goſpel Church;</hi> but they muſt be underſtood of the <hi>Faithful People of God,</hi> who through his Spirit are kept alive in a <hi>Teſtimony for Chriſt, againſt Antichriſt,</hi> during the time of the <hi>Beaſts Reign;</hi> That the People of God or ſuch of them as are kept alive by him are his <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> ſee <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.10. Chap. 44.8. And they are here called <hi>two; Firſt</hi> becauſe <hi>two</hi> according to Scripture, is a competent <hi>Number</hi> for <hi>VVitneſs;</hi> and <hi>Secondly</hi> their <hi>Teſtimony</hi> is <hi>two fold;,</hi> viz. for the <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> againſt <hi>the Civil,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Part of <hi>Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> theſe being the great <hi>Truths Witneſſed</hi> too, and <hi>contended</hi> for by thoſe that have been <hi>enlightned</hi> and kept alive for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and alſo the Truths which <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath moſt ſtruck at, and endeavoured ever ſince his <hi>Reign</hi> to Race out (if poſſible) from the <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> that ſo <hi>Himſelf</hi> might <hi>Reign</hi> alone; and this agrees with the <hi>Two Anointed Ones</hi> (to wit) <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> and the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,</hi> Zech. 4.11. To the <hi>Second thing</hi> (viz.) the <hi>Slaying.</hi> It muſt either be a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or a <hi>Corporal Slaying;</hi> It cannot be a <hi>Corporal Slaying; Firſt,</hi> becauſe they were ſo <hi>Slain</hi> in the time of their <hi>Propheſie in Sackcloth,</hi> but this <hi>Slaying</hi> being diſtinguiſhed, and taking place when they have <hi>finiſhed their Teſtimony,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be ſuch a <hi>Slaying</hi> as they did not partake of before; 2ly. It cannot be a <hi>Corporall Slaying,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Dead-Bodies lie in the ſtreets three Dayes and a Half,</hi> which muſt be <hi>Prophetical</hi> Dayes, <hi>a Day</hi> for a <hi>Year:</hi> for the <hi>Rejoycing and ſending of Gifts to one another,</hi> cannot be Accompliſht in ſo many natural <hi>Dayes,</hi> and if it muſt be <hi>Years,</hi> then the <hi>Slaying</hi> cannot be <hi>Corporal,</hi> for none may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that ſuch <hi>Dead Bodies</hi> ſhould <hi>lie</hi> ſo long <hi>in the ſtreets.</hi> 3dly. it cannot be a <hi>Corporal Slaying,</hi> If we conſider the <hi>Reſurrection of them,</hi> for it is not the natural <hi>life</hi> or <hi>ſpirit,</hi> that <hi>enters into them,</hi> but the <hi>Spirit of life from God;</hi> and if it be conſidered that there is <hi>a ſpace</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> in which they are <hi>Slaying,</hi> and alſo a <hi>Time</hi> of their <hi>Riſing</hi> and <hi>Standing upon their Feet,</hi> before they are <hi>Caught up to Heaven</hi> into the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> and both may be diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Three Years</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> of their <hi>Lying Dead,</hi> and that the <hi>Lord</hi> who never leaves <hi>Himſelf</hi> without <hi>Witneſſe</hi> will keep a Remnant alive to <hi>Bear</hi> up his <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> even whilſt the <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> are ſaid to <hi>Lie Dead</hi> in the Streets of the <hi>Great City,</hi> or <hi>Territories</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> which in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.18. is <hi>Called</hi> The <hi>Great City,</hi> and their <hi>Slaying</hi> being <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> and not <hi>Corporal,</hi> is moſt likely to take place after <hi>God</hi> hath begun to <hi>Reward Babylon;</hi> If this I ſay be conſidered, why may not this <hi>Tryal</hi> that is <hi>Come</hi> upon <hi>the VVork</hi> at this <hi>Day,</hi> and the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſlaughter</hi> that is come upon thoſe that have been <hi>VVitneſſes</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> agree with, and in a great meaſure anſwer to the <hi>Slaying</hi> of the <hi>VVitneſſes:</hi> For as hath been ſhewed, the <hi>Lord</hi> ſuffers not <hi>Babylon to drink</hi> more of <hi>Zions Blood,</hi> becauſe he hath begun <hi>to Reward Her.</hi> And as to the extraordinary things that the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> are ſaid to <hi>have Power</hi> to <hi>Do,</hi> in <hi>ſhutting Heaven,</hi> and <hi>ſmiting</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> &amp;c. I underſtand that it holds forth their <hi>Prevalency</hi> with <hi>God</hi> through
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192321:23"/>
               <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> not that we muſt needs expect thoſe <hi>ſeveral things</hi> to be done in the <hi>Letter,</hi> for it is not ſaid <hi>that they ſhall do them,</hi> but <hi>they have Power</hi> to do them Verſe 6, and no doubt but the <hi>Lords People</hi> that have been kept <hi>Faithful</hi> for him, have had <hi>Power as Princes to prevaile with him</hi> for <hi>Great Things,</hi> and he hath anſwered them <hi>by terrible things in Righteouſneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 65.5. But I ſhall ſay no more to this <hi>Objection,</hi> Though there are ſeveral other <hi>Objections</hi> againſt the <hi>VVork</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> as it hath taken place in this Nation, I ſhall not further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon them, being much perſwaded that the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of it is very near, in which God will wonderfully anſwer the <hi>Doubts</hi> and <hi>Objections</hi> of his <hi>Own People,</hi> and will <hi>ſtop the Mouths of Gain-ſayers,</hi> and <hi>Cloth the Enemies of his Son with ſhame,</hi> while <hi>the Children of Zion ſhall be rejoycing in their King,</hi> and <hi>ſinging Hoſanna to the Son of David,</hi> upon whom alone the <hi>Crown ſhall flouriſh,</hi> Pſal. 132.18.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not add more in this <hi>Matter,</hi> having ſpoken to the Several <hi>General Heads;</hi> But from what hath been laid down of the <hi>Work</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from it, The <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> by keeping their <hi>Places</hi> under <hi>Cromwell</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and not openly improving their <hi>Power</hi> to the hazzard of their all for <hi>Christ</hi> (who had formerly owned them) againſt the <hi>Apostates</hi> wicked <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> but declaring and improving their <hi>Power</hi> for the <hi>Apostacy</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (whoſe <hi>Cauſe</hi> they had engaged to own) they became guilty of <hi>Cromwels</hi> Abominations and the others that have Succeeded in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy:</hi> and comparing their Solemn <hi>Oaths, Covenants, Engagements</hi> and <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> made by them at their firſt taking up of <hi>Arms,</hi> and at the <hi>New Model</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> in 45, and at <hi>Naſeby, Triplo-Heath, Albanes, Putney</hi> and <hi>VVindſor:</hi> Alſo at their <hi>March</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> when they went to engage in that <hi>VVar,</hi> and at <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clebrough,</hi> and <hi>Dunbar</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> when they were brought very low, alſo at <hi>VVorceſter,</hi> and in the late War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and after <hi>VVorceſter,</hi> In their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn daies of Prayer at <hi>Jameſes,</hi> immediatly before the breaking up of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> with many other Solemn daies of Prayer: All theſe with many more <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements,</hi> which are beſt known to <hi>God</hi> and their <hi>Own Souls,</hi> being compared with their late <hi>Abominations</hi> in turning aſide with <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and engaging and ſtanding by the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Rich. Cromwel</hi> the Son of the <hi>Apostate,</hi> it is plain and manifeſt to all (that are not blinded through <hi>partaking</hi> with the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> or do not willfully ſhut their eyes, or through Careleſneſs or fearfulneſs, look not after theſe things) That the <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> with others who have kept their <hi>Places</hi> in the <hi>Apostacy</hi> are deeply Guilty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of <hi>Treachery</hi> in betraying the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> which is abundantly wrapped up therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of doing <hi>Injury</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by withſtanding and interrupting his <hi>Government</hi> in the Hands of his <hi>People,</hi> in the <hi>Little Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Of the higheſt <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> in Owning and Standing by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> in his <hi>Uſurping</hi> the very <hi>Throne of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They are Guilty of <hi>Theft</hi> or <hi>Robery,</hi> in not only Robbing <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:192321:23"/>
(as much as in them lay) of his <hi>Throne,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> of his <hi>Glory,</hi> but the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of its <hi>Treaſure,</hi> by forcing from them <hi>Taxes, Exciſe</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> to maintain the <hi>Apoſtacy:</hi> For though it may be lawful in a <hi>Lawful Magiſtracy</hi> to <hi>Raiſe Money</hi> in the <hi>Nation,</hi> to do the <hi>Nation</hi> ſervice, yet it is <hi>Robbery</hi> and <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> for a <hi>Uſurper</hi> that ſets himſelf both againſt <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Nation,</hi> to impoſe <hi>Taxes</hi> upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> They are guilty of <hi>Blood:</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which hath been a foot amongſt us, being the only <hi>Ground</hi> to Juſtifie, and clear the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> imployed in the <hi>War,</hi> from the <hi>Guilt</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> that hath been ſhed therein, and alſo of the <hi>Blood</hi> of the late <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Nobles,</hi> whoſe <hi>Heads</hi> were <hi>taken off;</hi> the Army and thoſe that have been engaged in the <hi>VVar,</hi> and are ſince turned aſide in the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> to the Diſowning and caſting off the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> muſt needs bring the <hi>Guilt</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> They are guilty of the breach of <hi>Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> and of <hi>Lying</hi> both to God and Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> They are guilty of the <hi>Perſecuting, Impriſoning,</hi> and <hi>Baniſhing</hi> the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who through free grace have been kept from the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and helped to Witneſs for the <hi>Righteous Cauſe of Chriſt</hi> againſt it, and although <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Councel,</hi> had the greateſt hand in the <hi>Apoſtacy:</hi> yet the <hi>Army</hi> in <hi>ſtanding</hi> by them, and <hi>putting</hi> their <hi>Commands</hi> in <hi>Execution,</hi> carrying the <hi>Saints</hi> to, and keeping them in <hi>Priſons,</hi> and that with much <hi>Heighth</hi> and <hi>Rage</hi> of <hi>Spirit,</hi> are <hi>involved</hi> in, and become <hi>Guilty</hi> of, the <hi>Evils</hi> with <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Through this <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> they are fallen into, and have embodyed themſelves with <hi>Babylon,</hi> or the <hi>Antichriſtian State,</hi> and have made themſelves as a Prop to the <hi>Whoriſh falſe Church,</hi> and did manifeſt this by ſetting up <hi>Tryers</hi> for <hi>Babylons Miniſters,</hi> and Keeping up the <hi>Univerſities</hi> or <hi>Schools</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> which is <hi>Babylons</hi> Maintenance, and alſo <hi>Babylons Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Courts,</hi> and many ſuch like <hi>Abominations,</hi> have been and are kept up by <hi>Cromwel</hi> and thoſe that have <hi>ſucceeded</hi> him in the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> through the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtatiſing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> without which they could not ſtand, and ſo the <hi>Guilt</hi> of theſe <hi>Evils</hi> falls upon the <hi>Army;</hi> theſe things not being done in a <hi>Corner,</hi> but <hi>Publiclky</hi> tranſacted in the <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the moſt of them being <hi>Publiſhed</hi> in <hi>Print</hi> to the <hi>World</hi> I ſhall not take up time to inſiſt more upon <hi>Partitulers,</hi> in the opening the <hi>Sins</hi> of the <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the <hi>Army;</hi> the moſt of theſe <hi>Great Evils</hi> being acted by the <hi>Army,</hi> as a Compact <hi>Body,</hi> (how ever ſome particular Perſons may think to excuſe themſelves) the <hi>Guilt</hi> (and except the Lord gives repentance) the <hi>Judgments</hi> due to theſe <hi>Abominations,</hi> is like to fall upon the <hi>Skirts</hi> of thoſe that have gone along in the <hi>Sins,</hi> though they have not been the <hi>Leaders,</hi> but the <hi>Followers;</hi> When <hi>Iſrael</hi> did <hi>Sin,</hi> and were <hi>Led</hi> into it by ſome particular Perſons, yet they as a <hi>People</hi> embodyed <hi>turning aſide,</hi> the <hi>Judgment</hi> was <hi>General</hi> that came upon them, as in the Matter of the <hi>Molton Calf,</hi> Exod. 32. <hi>Aaron</hi> was the great <hi>Tranſgreſſor,</hi> as Verſe 25. yet all that did not <hi>Separate</hi> and come to <hi>Moſes,</hi> were in danger of the <hi>Stroke,</hi> as Verſe 26, 27. When but <hi>Hezekiah</hi> 2 Chron. 32.35. had ſinned, <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being <hi>embodyed</hi> with him, the <hi>Wrath</hi> comes upon them, as well as on him; <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> was not the Ringleader in going to the <hi>Battel</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:192321:24"/>
at <hi>Ramoth-Gilead</hi> with <hi>Ahab,</hi> neither was the <hi>VVork</hi> in it ſelf unlawful, for <hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi> did of right belong to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and was kept from them by the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syria,</hi> yet but for joyning with <hi>Ahab</hi> who was turned from the Lord, <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> was ſharply reproved by the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and eſcaped very narrowly with his Life and wrath from the Lord was upon him. See 2 Chro. 18.1.31. Ch. 19.2. And though many poor <hi>Creatures</hi> have manifeſted <hi>Grief,</hi> and <hi>Spoke</hi> againſt <hi>Cromwel</hi> and others that were the <hi>Champions</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and yet have kept their <hi>Places</hi> either in the <hi>Army</hi> or elſewhere under it, and have not <hi>Separated</hi> from, nor improved their <hi>Power</hi> againſt it, will (as may be feared) be found in the <hi>day of Deciſion,</hi> helpers of the <hi>Mighty</hi> againſt the Lord, <hi>VVhen</hi> [Iſa. 31.2, 3.] <hi>he that helpeth and him that is holpen ſhall fall together, Then ſhall ye know, Num.</hi> 16.30. <hi>that this people have greatly provoked the Lord;</hi> If the <hi>Congregation</hi> obſerved not the <hi>Command</hi> Verſe 26. <hi>to depart from the Tents of thoſe wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs,</hi> they were like to be <hi>conſumed</hi> with them. And if they muſt be <hi>Curſed</hi> Judges 5.28. that <hi>Come not to the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty:</hi> How ſhall thoſe eſcape that <hi>help the Mighty against the Lord.</hi> And if <hi>Jeremiah</hi> Chap. 15. would not ſit in the <hi>Congregation</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but rather <hi>Sit</hi> alone, how ſhall thoſe think to <hi>Eſcape,</hi> that both <hi>Sit,</hi> and <hi>Act</hi> in the midſt of thoſe which not only <hi>Mock</hi> at, but have <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt,</hi> and ſet themſelves againſt the <hi>Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having been much larger upon theſe things then I did expect, I have for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſake, omitted ſeverall things that relate to this <hi>Latter day VVork,</hi> as alſo the ſpeaking to ſeverall <hi>Objections,</hi> which I deſire thoſe that <hi>ſeek for Knowledg as for hid Treaſure,</hi> may waite upon the Lord for <hi>Anſwers</hi> thereunto; and as for the Cavillers, I am not carefull to Anſwer them, but ſhall leave it to the <hi>Day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> and <hi>Revivall</hi> of the Lords <hi>VVork.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to Conclude the whole, I ſhall preſent to the true <hi>Favourers</hi> of this <hi>Deſpiſed Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſome <hi>Conſiderations</hi> by way of direction, and the Lord give them an underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Thing,</hi> is, To be much in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Anointing</hi> which as hath been ſhew'd is <hi>Reſerved</hi> for, and <hi>Promiſed</hi> to this <hi>VVork,</hi> and without which the <hi>VVork</hi> will not be accompliſhed, but thorough the <hi>Anointing</hi> it muſt be done.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Thing</hi> is, to be much in Looking after, Calling to mind, Prizing and Feeding upon the <hi>VVorks</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which he hath <hi>VVrought in the Mid'ſt of us,</hi> and comparing thoſe <hi>VVorks</hi> with the <hi>Promiſes, Propheſies</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> of the <hi>Latter day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Thing,</hi> is, To be <hi>Eying,</hi> and <hi>Reaching</hi> after, the underſtanding of the <hi>Glory</hi> of this <hi>Fifth Kingdome,</hi> and to be <hi>Talking</hi> of the <hi>Power</hi> of God, by which the <hi>VVork</hi> muſt be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth Thing,</hi> is, To be much in the Conſideration, of what <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath done for their <hi>Souls</hi> in the <hi>ſhedding</hi> of his <hi>Pretious Blood</hi> to <hi>Redeem</hi> them from <hi>Hell,</hi> and bring them to <hi>Glory,</hi> and that this <hi>Fifth Kingdome</hi> is given to <hi>Chriſt</hi> as a <hi>Reward</hi> to, and the <hi>Deſert</hi> of, what he hath <hi>Done</hi> and <hi>Suffer'd</hi> for them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth Thing,</hi> is, To be giveing unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Chief Seat</hi> in, and <hi>Sole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> over their own Souls, that ſo in all things they may be <hi>Conformable</hi> unto
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192321:24"/>
him, having their <hi>Converſations in Heaven,</hi> as thoſe that are <hi>Looking for, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening to,</hi> the <hi>Glorious</hi> Things which are to be <hi>brought forth</hi> in the <hi>Latter Day,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 11.14.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sixth Thing,</hi> is, To <hi>Come forth of,</hi> and <hi>Seperate from,</hi> whole <hi>Babylon,</hi> in all the <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Branches</hi> of it, and all the <hi>Parts</hi> of the <hi>Late Apoſtacy,</hi> upon which Gods diſpleaſure hath been and is eminently Manifeſted; and O that both my <hi>Self</hi> and all that <hi>Love Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and have in <hi>Days</hi> paſt <hi>touched</hi> with <hi>the unclean thing,</hi> may obtaine ſuch Repentance from the Lord, as to <hi>be Spared</hi> and <hi>Hid</hi> in this <hi>Day of his feirce Anger,</hi> when he is <hi>comming forth,</hi> and making himſelf <hi>Known by the Judgments which he Executeth:</hi> and as <hi>Noah</hi> found Grace, and <hi>Lot</hi> obtained <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> by which they were delivered from thoſe <hi>Judgments</hi> that were <hi>Executed</hi> in <hi>their Day:</hi> ſo thoſe that muſt be <hi>Saved</hi> for the <hi>King</hi> in this <hi>Day,</hi> muſt be ſaved thorough <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy;</hi> and ſeeing we <hi>ſtand by Faith, let us not be high-minded, but feare:</hi> and in this of <hi>Seperation,</hi> let it not ſuffice to <hi>Seperate</hi> from the <hi>Nationall</hi> Falſe <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Uſurpers</hi> of the <hi>Civill Power,</hi> in all the <hi>Parts</hi> of their <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtatiſing Army,</hi> by which the <hi>Uſurpation</hi> hath been <hi>Encouraged</hi> and <hi>Upheld,</hi> and from all <hi>Thoſe</hi> that have <hi>Kept,</hi> and do <hi>Keep Places</hi> under the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> or have been <hi>Turned out</hi> and not <hi>Repented of their Sin;</hi> But alſo from all thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Congregations,</hi> that have not <hi>Born</hi> their <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> againſt, but Contrariwiſe <hi>Fallen</hi> in with, and <hi>Encouraged</hi> the <hi>Apostacy,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>by Addreſſing</hi> to, or <hi>Standing</hi> by <hi>Thoſe</hi> that have ſo <hi>Betrayed</hi> the <hi>Cauſe of Christ,</hi> or by <hi>Keeping Communion</hi> in the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> n the <hi>Church</hi> with thoſe that have <hi>Stood</hi> by and <hi>Kept Places</hi> under the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> by which thoſe <hi>Churhes</hi> have brought upon <hi>Themſelves the Guilt of,</hi> and are become <hi>Partakers with other mens Sins,</hi> Contrary to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. And have <hi>Suffere Sin to lye upon their Brother,</hi> contrary to <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. And have deeply not only <hi>Touched,</hi> but <hi>Embraced</hi> the <hi>Unclean thing,</hi> contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. And have not <hi>depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Tents of thoſe Wicked men,</hi> according to <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.26. Nor been <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant for the Truth,</hi> as <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3. Nor <hi>ſtood up for the Lord againſt the evil doers</hi> according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.16. And have not <hi>frowned</hi> upon thoſe <hi>Members</hi> that have made themſelves Vild thorough the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 3.13. But have <hi>juſtified</hi> the <hi>Tranſgreſſors,</hi> and ſaid to the <hi>Apoſtates yea are Righteous, Pro.</hi> 17.15. <hi>chap.</hi> 24.24. They have not <hi>Turned away from the Traytors,</hi> as the ought to have done according to 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 4, 5. but have had <hi>fellowſhip with the unfruitfull Works of Darkneſs,</hi> and not <hi>reproved them,</hi> contrary to <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all theſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> that have ſo <hi>Turned aſide</hi> wi h the <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> have greatly <hi>Sinned againſt the Lord;</hi> and as a further <hi>A dition</hi> to there <hi>Evills,</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Leading Perſons</hi> of the <hi>Baptized Congregations</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> have ſet forth a <hi>Very Evil D claration,</hi> bearing <hi>Date</hi> the 12th of the 10th <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1659. which as appeares b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Title</hi> compared with the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſtſcript,</hi> they would have it be underſtood to comprehend the <hi>Ju gment</hi> of the <hi>Generality</hi> of the <hi>Baptized People;</hi> and although many <hi>Things</hi> in that <hi>Declaration</hi> is Manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory both to the <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Practiſe,</hi> of not only the <hi>Generality</hi> of the <hi>Baptized People,</hi> but even of <hi>Severall</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe</hi> whoſe <hi>Hands</hi> are to it, and the <hi>Evills</hi> of theſe <hi>Perſons</hi> made <hi>Obvious</hi> to the <hi>World:</hi> yet the <hi>Churches</hi> to whom
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192321:25"/>
they <hi>Relate</hi> have not <hi>Dealt</hi> with them, but rather <hi>Juſtified</hi> them in thoſe <hi>Evills,</hi> by which they become <hi>Partakers</hi> with them in thoſe <hi>Sins;</hi> and now thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> being <hi>Guilty</hi> of the <hi>Evils</hi> before mentioned, it is the <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>Lords Faithfull Remnant,</hi> whoſe eyes are open to ſee theſe <hi>Evils,</hi> after all due meanes that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Rule</hi> hath been <hi>Uſed</hi> for their <hi>Recovery,</hi> to <hi>Withdraw</hi> their <hi>Communion</hi> and <hi>Seperate</hi> from thoſe <hi>Churches,</hi> according to 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.14. <hi>Withdraw from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Brother that Walks Diſorderly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not the <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>Greater Number</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> in that <hi>Church</hi> (if they <hi>Walk Diſorderly,</hi>) that will exempt them from the <hi>Cenſure</hi> due to the <hi>Sin;</hi> When the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> turned aſide from the <hi>Lord: Jeremiah</hi> (though a Single Perſon) <hi>Seperates from them and Sets alone, chap.</hi> 15. 17. and the Lord doth ſo far ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of that Action of his, as that in Verſe 19. he ſaith, <hi>Let them return to thee, but return not thou unto them:</hi> Alſo in <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.26. When <hi>Iſrael had ſinned and turned aſide from the Lord</hi> in the Matter of the <hi>Molton Calf,</hi> Moſes <hi>ſtood in the Gate of the Camp and ſaid, Who is on the Lords ſide, let him come unto me.</hi> In the forementioned place of 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.5. <hi>Timothy</hi> though a ſingle perſon, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>turn away</hi> from the <hi>Evil Doers,</hi> and no doubt if a <hi>Whole Church</hi> come under the <hi>Guilt</hi> of thoſe <hi>Evils</hi> there mentioned, <hi>Timothy</hi> is not to abide with them becauſe they are a <hi>Church,</hi> there being no ſuch <hi>Limitation</hi> in the <hi>Command,</hi> but <hi>from ſuch</hi> he muſt <hi>turn away.</hi> I have formerly thought that a <hi>Particular Member</hi> might not <hi>Separate</hi> from a <hi>Church,</hi> till thorough ſin their <hi>Candlestick</hi> was taken away, but after waiting upon the Lord &amp; much <hi>ſearching the Scriptures,</hi> and through many <hi>Tryalls</hi> bearing my <hi>Burden,</hi> I have ſeen, that according to <hi>Rule,</hi> as there is a difference betwixt the <hi>VVithdrawing</hi> from, and the <hi>Cutting off of a Member:</hi> ſo there is a difference betwixt the <hi>Withdrawing</hi> from &amp; the <hi>Unchurching</hi> of a <hi>Church;</hi> and as a <hi>Church</hi> may <hi>Withdraw</hi> from a <hi>Brother</hi> without <hi>Cutting him off,</hi> or <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> him as a <hi>Heathen or</hi> a <hi>Publican,</hi> but ſtill <hi>to admoniſh him as a Brother,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.15. ſo a <hi>Brother</hi> for <hi>Sin</hi> committed by a <hi>Church,</hi> may <hi>withdraw</hi> from them, and yet not count them as <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Publicans;</hi> and though <hi>VVithdrawing</hi> be an <hi>Authoritative Act,</hi> as is alleadged, yet the <hi>Authority</hi> doth not of neceſſity reſt with the <hi>Greater Number,</hi> but with <hi>Truth,</hi> and where <hi>Truth is</hi> there is the <hi>Authority of Chriſt,</hi> Math. 16.18. <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth not <hi>Build</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> upon the <hi>Number,</hi> but upon the <hi>Truth</hi> which was with <hi>Peter,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Son of the Living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know it is objected, <hi>That in ſeveral of the Seven Churches</hi> in <hi>Aſia</hi> (mentioned Rev. 2. and 3. Chapters) <hi>though there was a great turning aſide, yet there were ſome kept faithful even in thoſe Places where the Churches were turned aſide, and we do not find that they were commanded to Separate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this is <hi>Twofold. Firſt,</hi> That though in <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> which are (as I think) the only <hi>Churches</hi> that can be inſtanced in this Matter, there were ſome kept <hi>Faithful</hi> even in thoſe <hi>Places,</hi> it will not follow, that becauſe they were in <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>Thyatira,</hi> which were the <hi>Places,</hi> in which thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> were, and theſe <hi>Faithful</hi> Ones were written to by <hi>John,</hi> that therefore they were in <hi>Communion</hi> with thoſe that had <hi>turned aſide</hi> from the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though we do not find they are expreſly commanded to <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:192321:25"/>
if they were in <hi>Communion</hi> by the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> that were written to them, yet it was ſufficient that there were ſuch <hi>Rules</hi> laid down in the <hi>Scripture</hi> which <hi>Rules</hi> they ought to look to, for there were ſeveral <hi>Churches</hi> that were written to by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and no mention made in the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> either of <hi>Baptiſm, Breaking</hi> of <hi>Bread,</hi> and ſeveral other <hi>Ordinances;</hi> but it will not therefore follow that thoſe <hi>Ordinances</hi> ought not ſtrictly to be obſerved by them, according to other <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Laſt thing</hi> that I ſhall preſent to thoſe that are <hi>Waiting</hi> for the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> is, to be giving up <hi>Themſelves</hi> and their <hi>All</hi> to the <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> accounting it a very great mercy if he ſhall <hi>Accept</hi> of, and <hi>Imbarque</hi> them with all their <hi>Concernments,</hi> in the <hi>Bottom</hi> with that <hi>Dear Cauſe,</hi> that ſo they may be <hi>Waiting</hi> at his <hi>Foot,</hi> till he ſhall <hi>Ariſe up to the prey,</hi> and blow the <hi>Trumpet</hi> giving them the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Command</hi> to <hi>gird on their Swords and Follow him</hi> in the <hi>Revival</hi> of his <hi>Work,</hi> and the further <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Judgements written:</hi> in which <hi>Day</hi> they ſhall undoubtedly <hi>Reap</hi> the bleſſed <hi>Fruit</hi> of all their <hi>Labour, Service,</hi> and <hi>Tryals,</hi> that they either have, or may yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undergo for him. <hi>In due ſeaſon we ſhall reap if we faint not,</hi> Gal. 6.9. <hi>They that ſow in Tears, ſhall reap in Joy,</hi> Pſal. 126.5. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty,</hi> Iſai. 33.17. <hi>Let the Children of Zion be joyful in their King,</hi> Pſal. 149.2. <hi>Let them ſhout for joy and be glad, that favour my Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Cauſe,</hi> Pſal. 35.27. And it <hi>ſhall be ſaid</hi> in that day, <hi>Lo this our God we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation,</hi> Iſai. 25.9.</p>
            <p>And thus I have according to the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> received, <hi>Preſented</hi> unto <hi>Thee,</hi> with the reſt of my <hi>Friends</hi> in <hi>Communion</hi> with thee that are <hi>Waiting</hi> for the <hi>Coming</hi> of <hi>Zions King,</hi> my Underſtanding in theſe <hi>Matters</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom:</hi> and I deſire but ſo much favour from you as <hi>Paul</hi> obtained from the <hi>Bereans,</hi> and when you have ſeriouſly <hi>Weighed</hi> the <hi>ſeveral Things</hi> contained in this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> in the <hi>Ballance of the Sanctuary:</hi> wherein I may appear to be in the <hi>Dark</hi> or <hi>Miſtaken</hi> about theſe <hi>Great Matters,</hi> be <hi>Earneſt</hi> with the <hi>Lord</hi> for me, that my <hi>Miſtakes</hi> may be rectified and my <hi>Judgement</hi> rightly <hi>Informed,</hi> for I deſire I may not through <hi>Errour</hi> ſerve the <hi>Deſign of Satan,</hi> But that I may by the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> be led <hi>into all Truth,</hi> and ſo ſerve my <hi>Dear Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who <hi>Loved me</hi> a Vild Wretch, <hi>and ſhed his Precious Blood for me:</hi> and if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any <hi>Benefit</hi> by theſe <hi>Things,</hi> let <hi>Chriſt</hi> my <hi>King</hi> bear the <hi>Glory</hi> according to <hi>Iſai.</hi> 22.24. <hi>Zech.</hi> 6.13. And now I ſhall <hi>Commit</hi> you, with theſe <hi>Things</hi> to the <hi>Bleſſing of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>Cloſe</hi> with that <hi>Word</hi> in 2 Tim. 2.7. <hi>Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give thee underſtanding in all Things.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I remain through grace <hi>thy B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>other and Servant in the Kingdom and Patience of Chriſt.</hi> N. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:192321:26"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SEveral Friends having Knowledge of this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and earneſtly deſiring <hi>Copies</hi> of it, more then could well be <hi>Tranſcribed;</hi> I have for <hi>them</hi> and <hi>Others</hi> of my <hi>Friends</hi> both in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> Cauſed ſeveral of them to be <hi>Printed;</hi> But conſidering my own <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> and the many <hi>Books</hi> that have been <hi>Publiſhed</hi> about theſe <hi>Matters,</hi> I have not been willing to <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> this to the <hi>World,</hi> but only to preſent it to ſuch of my <hi>Acquaintance</hi> that <hi>Love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity,</hi> ſome of them being far <hi>Remote</hi> in the <hi>Countrys,</hi> that I cannot as yet viſit <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>Others</hi> in ſuch <hi>Churches,</hi> where by <hi>Reaſon</hi> of my <hi>Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> in theſe <hi>Matters</hi> of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> I am <hi>debarred</hi> of my <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Preaching</hi> to them; and the <hi>Lord</hi> make this <hi>Service</hi> (ſo far as it ſhall really appear to be for his <hi>Glory</hi> and their <hi>Good) Acceptable</hi> and <hi>Succeſsful</hi> to them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:192321:26"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192321:27"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>The <hi>END.</hi>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
